【いい】

1. いい

a. いい〈praise〉

（1）そのセーターいいですね。よく似合 ってますよ。／That’s a nice sweater. It suits you very well.

（2）A:彼女 、新婚 旅行 ギリシャだって。／I heard she is going to Greece for her honeymoon.

B:へえ、いいなあ。／Really? That sounds nice.

This is used when one expresses praise or envy. Combines with ね or なあ.

b. いい〈refusal〉

（1）A:もう一杯 どうですか。／Would you like another cup of tea?

B:いえ、もういいです。／No, thank you.

（2）A:ケーキがあるんだけど食 べない？／Do you want some cake?

B:いや、今 はいい。／Not now, thanks.

In these cases, いい is used to refuse an offer. It has the same meaning as けっこうです.

c. いい〈call someone’s attention to something〉

（1）いいね、今 言 ったことは誰 にもしゃべっちゃだめだよ。／Listen, you can’t tell anyone what I said just now.

（2）いい、よく見 ててね。ここを押 すとスイッチが切 れるから、それからコンセントを抜 いてね。／OK now, look carefully—pressing here turns it off, and then pull the plug out. Got it?

（3）いいか、よく聞 け。これからは俺 がこのグループのリーダーだ。／Listen up, everyone. I am the leader of this group from now on.

（4）このグラフを見 てください。いいですか。これは 2001 年 までの世界 の人口 増加 を表 したものです。／Look at this graph, please. All right? This shows the increase in population in the world up to 2001.

Pronounced with a rising tone. Used to get the listener’s attention before giving an order or making a strong request, and to make sure that he/she is ready to listen.

d. いいから／いいよ

（1）A:私 があと3分 早 く着 いていれば乗 り遅 れることもなかったのですが...。／If I had arrived just three minutes earlier, we wouldn’t have missed it.

B:もうそのことはいいから。それより今 からどうしたらいいかを考 えましょう。／Oh, that’s OK. Let’s think about what we should do now.

（2）A:あ、タクシー1台 来 ました。どうぞ乗 って下 さい。次 がいつ来 るかもわかりませんし。／Here comes a taxi. Please take it. I’m not sure when another one will come.

B:いや、いいからどうぞ先 に乗 ってください。そちらの方 が遠 いんですから。／No, I’ll be all right, you go ahead. You have to go farther than I do.

（3）A:ねえ、そんな道 に入 って行 って大丈夫 なの？　迷 ったらどうするのよ。／Hey, is it all right to take such a road? What if we get lost?

B:いいからまかせとけって。こっちの方 が近道 なんだから。／It’s OK, just leave it to me. This is a shortcut.

（4）A:あ、数字 の入力 はそのキーじゃなくてこっちだよ。／Wait, you should use this key to enter numbers, not that one.

B:いいから、黙 っててよ。／Yes, yes, just shut up.

（5）A:私 がちゃんと財布 を鞄 の中 にしまっておけば、とられたりはしなかったのよね。クレジットカードだって別 のところに入 れておくべきだった。ガイドブックにもそうしろって書 いてあったし...。私 が悪 いのよ。／If I had put my wallet away in my bag, I wouldn’t have had it stolen. I should’ve kept my credit cards in another place. I remember the guidebook said to do that. This is my fault.

B:もういいよ。後悔 したって始 まらない。／It’s over and done with now. It’s a little late for regrets.

These express “You don’t have to say or think such a thing” about something the other person has said. They have the function of ending discussion and not letting the other person says anything more. (1), (2), and (3) are cases when the speaker wants to lighten up the situation, cheer up the other person, or say not to worry. (4) is a case when the speaker wants the other person to keep quiet because his/her concern is rather too much, and (5) means “There is no point in saying such a thing.” いいから means “You don’t have to worry about it; just keep quiet,” and it emphasizes putting a stop to the other person’s comments.

2. ...がいい

（1）悪 いことばかり覚 えて、お前 なんか、そのうち警察 に捕 まるがいいよ。／You learn only the bad things—someday the police ought to arrest you.

（2）悪 い奴 らはみんな悪魔 にとりつかれて死 んでしまうがいい。／All evil people should be possessed by a demon and die.

Expresses the speaker’s wish to bestow ill fortune on someone. Used to express criticism, to abuse, or to curse. An old-fashioned way of speaking.

3. ...ていい→【ていい】

4. ...といい→【といい】

【いか】

1. 数 量 詞 +いか

（1）なるべく4人以下 でグループを作 ってください。／If possible, please form a group of no more than four.

（2）500 グラム以下 のパックは 50円 引 きです。／Packs containing 500 grams and under are 50 yen off.

（3）3000 円 以下 で何 か記念品 を買 うとしたら、どんなものがあるでしょうか。／If we are to buy some sort of memento for under 3,000 yen, what kind of thing can we buy?

Indicates “the number/amount stated or fewer/less.”

2. Nいか

（1）中学生 以下 は入場 無料 です。／Admission is free for junior high school students and younger.

（2）中型 以下 の車 ならこの道 を通 ることができる。／Any vehicle that is medium-sized or smaller can take this road.

（3）B4サイズ以下 のものでないとこの機械 ではコピーできない。／Unless the paper size is B4 or smaller, you can’t make copies on this machine.

When いか follows a noun that is part of an order or sequence, or shows the degree of some attribute, it indicates something at or below the position or degree of N.

3. Nいかだ

（1）おまえはゴキブリ以下 だ。／You are lower than a cockroach.

（2）そんなひどい仕打 ちをするとは、あいつは人間 以下 だ。／To treat someone that cruelly makes him subhuman.

（3）まったくあいつの頭 ときたら小学生 以下 だ。／That guy hasn’t got the brains of a schoolchild!

Asserts that someone or something is lower than the person or thing represented by N. Used when one criticizes or slanders someone.

4. Nいか+数 量 詞

（1）わが社 では、社長 以下 約 300 人 が全員 一丸 となって働 いています。／In our company, everyone—including the president and about 300 employees—has joined forces to work together.

（2）山田 キャプテン以下 38 名 、全員 そろいました。／Captain Yamada and 38 members—everyone is here.

（3）その企業 グループは、ABC社 以下 12 社 で構成 されている。／This corporate group consists of ABC company and twelve other companies.

Used when describing a group that is led or represented by the person or thing referred to by the noun. When N is a person, a job title rather than an individual name is used. Used in written language and formal spoken language.

5. いか

（1）以下 同文 。／The rest of the text is the same as in the previous document.

（2）詳細 は以下 のとおりです。／The details are as follows.

Refers to the part following the present point in a written text or a speech. Usually used in written language.

【いったん...と】

（1）彼女 はおしゃべりな人 で、いったん話 し出 すと止 まらない。／She is a very talkative person; once she starts to talk, she never stops.

（2）いったんテレビゲームを始 めると2時間 ぐらいはすぐに経 ってしまう。／Once I start to play a video game, two hours or so pass very quickly.

（3）いったんこの段階 まで快復 すれば、後 はもう大丈夫 だ。／Once you recover to this level, then you’ll be all right.

（4）このお菓子 はいったんふたを開 けるとすぐに湿 ってしまうので、早 く食 べなければならない。／These sweets get soggy right away once the lid is opened, so we have to eat them quickly.

（5）いったんこんなゆとりのある生活 に慣 れてしまったら、もう前 のような忙 しい生活 には戻 れない。／Once you get used to a laid-back lifestyle like this, you can’t go back to the busy life you used to have.

たら and ば may also be used instead of と. Means that once changes take place, or things begin changing, it is not possible to return to the original state.

【がさいご】

［V-たがさいご］

（1）ここで会 ったが最後 、謝 ってもらうまでは逃 がしはしない。／Now that I’ve met you here, I won’t let you go until you apologize to me.

（2）この計画 を聞 いたが最後 、あなたもグループに加 わってもらおう。／Now that you’ve heard about this project, we’ll have you join the group.

（3）学校内 でタバコを吸 っているのを見 つかったが最後 、停学 は免 れないだろう。／Now that they’ve been found smoking in school, they won’t be able to avoid suspension.

（4）その茶碗 は、一度 手 に取 ったが最後 、どうしても買 わずにはいられなくなるほど手触 りや重 さ、色合 いなどが私 の好 みに合 っていた。／Once I had picked up the bowl I couldn’t help buying it, since its feel, weight, and color were so much to my liking.

Expresses that a certain event occurs as the consequence of someone’s action or a course of events indicated in the subsequent clause. Example (1) expresses a challenge, meaning “I met you here, so you shall apologize to me.” Example (2) has the imperative meaning “because you have heard about this project, you have to join the group.” Also used in general, in non-threatening, non-imperative sentences such as (3) and (4).

【かならずしも...ない】

（1）金持 ちがかならずしもしあわせだとは限 らない。／The rich are not necessarily happy.

（2）語学 が得意 だからといって、かならずしも就職 に有利 だとは限 らない。／Being good at languages doesn’t always give you an advantage in finding employment.

（3）日本人 は礼儀正 しい人々 だと言 う人 もいるようだが、実態 は必 ずしもそうではないとわたしは思 っている。／Some people say the Japanese people are polite, but I don’t think that is always the case.

（4）政治家 たちは国連 は重要 だと言 う。しかし、必 ずしも、常 に尊重 しなければならぬものだと思 っているわけではない。／Politicians say that the United Nations is important. But they don’t necessarily think it has to be respected at all times.

Means that the logical relationship “if X, then invariably Y” does not always apply. For example, (2) means that the proposition 語学が得意なら就職に有利だ (being good at languages is advantageous for getting a job) is not always true. かならずしも is often used with わけではない and とはかぎらない. It has the flavor of written language.

【げんざい】

（1）彼 が死 んでしまった現在 、もうそんなことを言 っても意味 がないよ。／Now that he’s dead, it’s meaningless to say such a thing.

（2）失敗 の原因 が明 らかになった現在 、われわれは何 をすべきか。／Now that the cause of the failure has been clarified, what should we do?

（3）あの改革案 がいまだに大方 の賛同 を得 られていない現在 、新 たな方策 を考 えておくことも重要 なことではないか。／At this time, when that proposal for reform has not yet gained general support, isn’t it important to consider new measures?

（4）地球 環境 の保護 が叫 ばれている現在 、クリーンエネルギーの夢 を広 げるその計画 への期待 は大 きい。／Now, when people are clamoring for protection of the global environment, expectations regarding that plan to expand the dream of clean energy are great.

Originally a noun, as in 過去と現在 (past and present) and 現在の気温は 29 度だ (the current temperature is 29 degrees). When attached to the end of a clause, it becomes an expression to present the current situation and then state an assertion on the part of the speaker. A formal expression that tends to be used in written language.

【ことになっている】

［Nということになっている］

［V-る　（という）ことになっている］

［V-ない　（という）ことになっている］

（1）やすむときは学校 に連絡 しなければならないことになっています。／There is a rule that you must contact the school when you are absent.

（2）乗車券 をなくした場合 は最長 区間 の料金 をいただくことになっているんですが。／I'm afraid that, when you’ve lost your train ticket, we have to ask you to pay the fare for the maximum distance.

（3）規則 では、不正 をおこなった場合 は失格 ということになっている。／According to the regulations, when you commit an act of wrongdoing, you will be disqualified.

（4）駐車場 内 での盗難 や事故 については、駐車場 側 は関知 しないことになっております。／The parking lot management takes no responsibility for theft or accidents that take place inside the parking lot.

（5）パーティーに参加 する人 は、6時 に駅 で待 ち合 わせることになっている。／Those who are going to attend the party are supposed to meet at the station at six o’clock.

（6）夏休 みのあいだ、畑 の水 やりは子供 たちがすることになっている。／During summer vacation, it’s the children's job to water the garden.

Indicates a variety of rules that govern people’s activities, including their plans, agreements in daily life, laws and rules, and even customs. Can be considered to mean that the conclusion or result of ...ことになる continues to have an effect.

【さあ】

1. さあ

（1）さあ、いこう。／All right, let’s go.

（2）さあ、いそいで、いそいで。／Come on, hurry up, hurry up.

（3）さあ、がんばるぞ。／OK, I’ll do my best.

（4）さあ、春 だ。／Now, it is spring.

（5）さあ、ごはんができたぞ。／Now dinner is ready.

Used to urge or invite the listener to do something. (3) is an example of someone encouraging him/herself. In cases like (4) and (5), the functions seen in (1), (2), and (3), such as urging, inviting, or encouraging someone to do something, are concealed. These examples can be paraphrased as さあ、春だ。がんばるぞ (Now, it is spring. I will work hard!) and さあ、ごはんができたぞ。食べよう／食べなさい (Now, dinner is ready. Let’s eat!/Start eating!). With the exception of the usage shown in (3), さあ can also be used by itself when the meaning is clear from the situation.

2. さあ

（1）A:あの人 、だれ？／Who is that person?

B:さあ（、知 りません）。／Well... (I don’t know).

（2）A:これから、どうする？／What are you going to do from now on?

B:さあ、どうしようかな。／Well, I’m not sure yet.

Used in response to a question or a situation when the speaker does not know the answer, as in (1), or when the speaker has trouble making a judgment, as in (2). さあ is used by itself, particularly with the meaning shown in (1), only when the conversation is between people in a close relationship.

【しかも】

［N／Na　でしかも］

［A-くてしかも］

（1）いいアパートを見 つけた。部屋 が広 くて、南向 きでしかも駅 から歩 いて5分 だ。／I found a good apartment. The rooms are spacious, it faces south, and what’s more it’s only a five-minute walk from the station.

（2）通訳 の採用枠 二名 に対 し百人 近 い応募 があったが、その九割 が女性 で、しかも半数 以上 は留学 経験者 だった。／There were nearly a hundred applicants for the two openings for interpreters, of whom ninety percent were female, and more than the half of them had studied abroad.

（3）若 くて、きれいで、しかも性格 がいいとなれば結婚 したがる男 はいくらでもいるだろう。／I would think that there are any number of men who would like to marry someone who is young and pretty and has a good personality to boot.

（4）彼女 は仕事 が速 くて、しかも間違 いが少 ないので上司 の信頼 が厚 い。／She’s a fast worker and also makes few mistakes, so her boss places a lot of trust in her.

（5）A:会社 の近 くで安 くておいしい店 、知 ってるんだって。／I hear you know a restaurant close to the office that's cheap and delicious.

B:うん、しかもすいてるんだよ。／Yeah, and what's more, it isn’t crowded.

（6）この不況 で会社 は昇給 なし、しかもボーナスは例年 の半分 になった。／Because of the recession, there have been no salary increases at the company, and on top of that, the bonus is half as much as in past years.

Used when describing something, to add another condition with a similar tendency. Means “on top of that, in addition.”

【ずにはいられない】

［V-ずにはいられない］

（1）この本 を読 むと、誰 でも感動 せずにはいられないだろう。／Anyone who reads this book will surely be moved by it, I think.

（2）彼女 の気持 ちを思 うと、自分 のしたことを悔 やまずにはいられない。／When I consider her feelings, I can’t help but feel regret for what I did.

（3）彼女 の美 しさには誰 でも魅了 されずにはいられなかった。／No one could help but be captivated by her beauty.

（4）会社 でのストレスを解消 するために酒 を飲 まずにはいられない。／To relieve the stress at my workplace, I can’t do without alcohol.

（5）その冗談 にはどんなまじめな人 も笑 わずにはいられないだろう。／I don’t think anyone, no matter how serious, could help but laugh at that joke.

Means that someone does something in spite of him/herself, or in spite of his/her determination to suppress it. Tends to be used in written language. In spoken language, it takes the form ...ないではいられない.

【せっかく】

1. せっかく...からには

（1）せっかく留学 するからには、できる限 り多 くの知識 を身 につけて帰 りたい。／Since I’m going abroad to study, I’d like to return having gained as much knowledge as I can.

（2）せっかく代表 として選 ばれたからには、全力 を尽 くさなければならない。／I must do my very best, since I was chosen to be the representative.

（3）せっかく休暇 をとるからには、2日 や3日 でなく、10日 ぐらいは休 みたい。／If I’m taking a vacation, I’d like to take at least ten days or so off, not just two or three.

Used in the pattern せっかくXからにはY. X is an action that involves effort, hardship, or a rare opportunity, and Y indicates the speaker’s desire to use such an effort or opportunity effectively. Expressions of intention, hope, advice, etc. are used in Y.

2. せっかく...けれども

（1）せっかくここまできたけれども、雨 がひどくなってきたから引 き返 そう。／I know we’ve come all this way, but it’s starting to rain harder, so let’s head back.

（2）せっかく皆 さんに骨折 っていただきましたが、実 はこの計画 は取 りやめになりました。／Although you have all worked so hard, I’m afraid this plan has been canceled.

（3）せっかく作 ったのですが、喜 んではもらえなかったようです。／Despite all the effort I put into making this, it doesn’t seem to have been appreciated.

Used in patterns like せっかくXけれどもY and せっかくXがY. X is an action that involves effort, hardship, or a rare opportunity. Y indicates that such an action has been wasted and expresses the speaker’s feeling of sorrow or regret for the waste.

3. せっかく...のだから

（1）せっかく来 たのだから夕飯 を食 べて行 きなさい。／Since you’ve come all this way, have supper before you go.

（2）せっかくここまで努力 したのだから、最後 までやり通 しましょう。／We’ve worked so hard to get this far, so let’s see it through to the end.

（3）せっかくおしゃれをしたのだから、どこかいいレストランへ行 きましょうよ。／I went to the trouble of getting all dressed up, so let’s go to a nice restaurant somewhere.

When せっかく is used in the pattern せっかくX（の）だからY, X is an action that involves effort, hardship, or a rare opportunity, and Y indicates the speaker’s desire to use such an effort or opportunity effectively. Expressions of intention, hope, request, invitation, advice, etc. are used in Y.

4. せっかく...のだったら

（1）せっかくピアノを習 うのだったら、少 しくらい高 くてもいい先生 についた方 がいい。／If I’m going to learn to play the piano, I may as well find a good teacher, even if it costs a little more.

（2）せっかく京都 まで行 くのなら、奈良 にも行 ってみたらどうですか。／If you’re going all the way to Kyoto, why not go to Nara as well?

（3）せっかく音楽 を楽 しむのだったら、もうすこし音 のいいステレオを買 いたい。／If I’m going to amuse myself by listening to music, I’d like to buy a stereo with better sound quality.

Used in patterns like せっかくXのだったらY or せっかくX（の）ならY. Indicates the speaker’s expectation that, if someone gets a rare opportunity or makes an effort to do something, it would be best to make the most of that opportunity or effort. Expressions that indicate intention, hope, advice, etc. are used in Y.

5. せっかく　...のに／...ても

（1）せっかく招待 していただいたのに、伺 えなくてすみません。／I was glad to receive your kind invitation, but I’m sorry I won’t be able to visit.

（2）せっかくいい天気 なのに、かぜをひいてどこにも行 けない。／Despite the nice weather, I can’t go anywhere because I’ve caught a cold.

（3）せっかくセーターを編 んであげたのに、どうも気 にいらないようだ。／Even though I went to the effort of knitting a sweater for him, he doesn’t seem to like it.

（4）せっかく来 ていただいても何 もお話 しすることはありません。／I don’t have anything to say to you, even if you make the effort to come all the way here.

（5）今回 のクイズには多数 のおはがきをお寄 せいただきました。ただせっかくお送 りいただきましても、締切日 をすぎておりますものは抽選 できませんのでご了承 ください。／Thank you for the many postcards we’ve received for this quiz. However, please understand that those sent after the deadline cannot be used in the draw.

The patterns せっかくXのにY and せっかくXてもY have the same meaning as せっかく...けれども. ...のに shows that X refers to a situation that has been realized, and ...ても shows that X refers to a hypothetical situation.

6. せっかくのN

（1）せっかくの日曜日 なのに、一日中 、雨 が降 っている。／Here it is Sunday, and wouldn’t you know it, it’s raining all day.

（2）せっかくのチャンスを逃 してしまった。／I let a rare opportunity slip away.

（3）せっかくの努力 が水 の泡 になってしまった。／All my efforts came to nothing.

（4）せっかくのごちそうなのだから、残 さないで全部 食 べましょう。／Since it’s such a feast, let’s eat it all up and not leave a crumb.

Used with nouns that describe an action involving a fortunate opportunity or an effort. Expresses a feeling of regret for not being able to utilize the opportunity/effort, or a feeling of hope or expectation that it should be utilized.

7. せっかく+連 体 修 飾 句 +N

（1）せっかく書 いた原稿 をなくしてしまった。／I’ve lost the draft that I worked so hard to write.

（2）せっかく覚 えた英語 も今 は使 う機会 がない。／Despite the effort I put into learning English, I have no opportunity to use it now.

（3）せっかくきれいに咲 いた花 をだれかが取 っていった。／Someone plucked the flower that was blooming so beautifully.

（4）せっかく作 った料理 を誰 も食 べてくれない。／Despite the effort I put into cooking this meal, no one’s eating it.

Indicates an action made possible by good fortune or one’s own efforts. Expresses a feeling of regret for not being able to utilize the opportunity/effort, or a feeling of hope or expectation that it should be utilized.

8. せっかくですが

（1）A:もう遅 いですから、泊 まっていらしたらいかがですか。／It’s already late, so why don’t you stay overnight?

B:せっかくですが、あしたは朝 から用事 がありますので。／Thank you, but tomorrow I have things to do starting in the morning.

（2）A:今晩 一緒 に食事 しない？／Shall we have dinner together tonight?

B:せっかくだけど、今晩 はちょっと都合 が悪 いんだ。／Thanks, but tonight’s just not convenient.

せっかくですが and せっかくだけど are used to preface the refusal of an offer or proposal made by someone else.

9. せっかくですから

（1）A:食事 の準備 がしてありますので、うちで召 し上 がってくださいよ。／Dinner is ready, so by all means, please stay and eat with us.

B:せっかくですから、お言葉 に甘 えて、そうさせていただきます。／That’s very kind of you. I will take you up on your generous offer.

（2）せっかくだから、あなたの作 ったケーキご馳走 になって行 くわ。／Since you went to all the trouble of baking a cake, I won’t leave without trying it.

Used to preface the acceptance of an offer or proposal made by someone else.

【そうすると】

1. そうすると〈opportunity〉

（1）ビルのまわりを回 ってみた。そうすると、ひとつだけ電気 のついている窓 があった。／I went around the building. When I did so, I found just one window with a light on.

（2）切符 はまとめて20人分 予約 することにした。そうすると、少 し割 り引 きがあって助 かるのだ。／I decided to reserve twenty tickets all at once. You get a bit of a discount that way, which helps.

（3）テニスの練習 は土曜日 の朝 することにしよう。そうすると、土曜日 の午後 は、時間 ができる。／I’ll practice tennis on Saturday morning. Then I’ll have some free time in the afternoon.

Means that a later event occurs or is noticed as the result of an earlier event or action. そうすると cannot be followed by expressions indicating an intentional act of the speaker.

（×）20人以上予約して下さい。そうすると割引きしましょう。／Please book for twenty people or more. Then let’s give you a discount.

In addition, the second sentence often expresses an interpretation of the event described in the first sentence.

2. そうすると〈consequence〉

（1）A:ホテルを出 るのが5時 で、新幹線 に乗 るのが6時 です。／We’re leaving the hotel at five o’clock, and taking the shinkansen (bullet train) at six.

B:そうすると、買 い物 の時間 がなくなりますよ。／But then we won’t have any time for shopping!

（2）A:お客 の数 が百 から二百 に増 えそうなんですが。／It looks like the number of guests might increase from 100 to 200.

B:そうすると、この会場 ではできなくなりますね。／In that case, we can’t hold it in this venue, can we.

（3）A:パスポートはおととし取 りました。／I got a passport the year before last.

B:そうすると、来年 はまだ大丈夫 ですね。／So, it will still be valid next year.

Used to make a statement in response to something the previous speaker has said. そうすると is followed by an interpretation of what the other person has said, a logical conclusion, etc. Roughly equivalent to すると. Used in spoken language.

【それでこそ】

（1）彼 は部下 の失敗 の責任 をとって、社長 の座 を降 りた。それでこそ真 のリーダーと言 える。／He took responsibility for his subordinate’s mistake and stepped down as company president. That’s what we can call a true leader.

（2）A:あの大学 、卒業 するのがむずかしいそうだよ。／I’ve heard that university is hard to graduate from.

B:それでこそ本当 の大学 だね。／That’s how a real university should be.

（3）A:今度 のコピー機 は、まったく人手 がいらないそうだ。／I hear the new photocopier doesn’t need anyone to operate it at all.

B:それでこそオフィス革命 と言 えるね。今 までのは人 を忙 しくさせるだけだったから。／You can call that a real office revolution, can’t you. Up till now it had just made people even busier.

Used at the beginning of a sentence, this means “because of, for that reason.” Used to highlight a certain quality of a person or thing and express a high evaluation of that person/thing, based on the previously-stated reason. Used only for positive evaluation. An old-fashioned expression. In conversation, it is often used in semi-formulaic expressions such as それでこそ本当のNだ (that’s a real/true N.)

【それとも】

1. NそれともN

（1）A:コーヒー？　それとも紅茶 ？／Coffee? Or tea?

B:どちらでもけっこうです。／Either one is fine.

（2）A:あしたのパーティーには、何 を着 て行 くつもり？　着物 、それともドレス？／What are you going to wear to the party tomorrow? A kimono, or a dress?

B:まだ、決 めてないのよ。／I haven’t decided yet.

（3）進学 か、それとも就職 かとずいぶん悩 んだ。／Going to graduate school, or finding a job—I worried a lot about which to do.

Takes the pattern XそれともY or XかそれともYか and means “either X or Y.” Used to indicate two possibilities and ask the listener which is better, as in (1), or to ask about the listener’s intention, as in (2). Cannot be used when giving instructions, as seen in the examples below.

（×）黒それとも青のインクで書いてください。／Please use a pen with black, or blue ink.

（○）黒か青のインクで書いてください。／Please use a pen with black or blue ink.

Also used when there are two possibilities and the speaker is unsure or doesn’t know which one to choose, as in (3). In this case, それとも can be replaced by あるいは (or).

2. ...それとも

（1）雨 が降 ってきましたが、どうしますか。行 きますか。それとも延期 しますか。／It’s started raining, so what shall we do? Shall we go? Or shall we postpone it?

（2）洋室 がよろしいですか、それとも和室 の方 がよろしいですか。／Would you prefer a Western-style room, or would a Japanese-style room be better?

（3）A:散歩 にでも行 く？　それとも、映画 でも見 ようか。／Do you want to take a walk? Or would you like to see a film?

B:そうね、久 しぶりに映画 もいいな。／Hmm... a movie might be nice, since we haven’t seen one in a while.

（4）就職 しようか、それとも進学 しようかと迷 っている。／I can’t decide whether to find a job or to go on to university.

（5）彼 は、初 めから来 るつもりがなかったのか、それとも、急 に気 が変 わったのか、約束 の時間 が過 ぎても現 れなかった。／I don’t know if he didn’t intend to come in the first place, or if he all of a sudden changed his mind, but he never showed up, even after the appointed time.

（6）この手紙 を読 んで、彼女 は喜 んでくれるだろうか。それとも、軽蔑 するだろうか。／I wonder if she’ll be happy when she reads this letter. Or if she’ll despise me.

Takes the pattern XそれともY or XかそれともYか and means “either X or Y.” (1)-(3) are examples of the speaker indicating two possibilities and asking the listener which is better. (4)-(6) are examples in which there are two possibilities, and the speaker is either unsure which is true or doesn’t know which to choose. In (4)-(6), それとも can be replaced by あるいは (or).

【それにしても】

（1）A:予選 ではあんなに強 かったのにどうして決勝 で負 けたんでしょうね。／He was so good in the preliminaries—I wonder why he lost in the final.

B:プレッシャーでしょう。／Probably due to pressure.

A:それにしてもひどい負 け方 ですね。／Even so, he really lost badly.

（2）A:坂本 さん、あの高校 に受 かったんだってね。／I hear Sakamoto-san passed the exam to get into that high school.

B:必死 で勉強 してたらしいよ。／Apparently she studied really hard for it.

A:それにしてもすごいね。／Even so, that’s really something!

（3）A:またガソリン代 、値上 がりしたよ。／The cost of gasoline has gone up again.

B:それにしても政治家 はなにをしてるんだろう。われわれがこんなに苦 しんでいるのに。／And what are the politicians doing about it? While we’re struggling so hard.

（4）A:太郎 、また背 がのびたようよ。／Taro seems to have grown more.

B:それにしても、あいつはよく寝 るなあ。／Even so (even though children who sleep well grow well), he really does sleep a lot, doesn’t he.

（5）《A、Bが竹下 さんを待 っている》／《A and B are waiting for Takeshita-san》

A:よく降 りますね。／It’s really raining hard, isn’t it?

B:ええ、それにしても竹下 さん遅 いですね。／Yes, but even so, Takeshita-san is quite late, isn’t he?

Means “even taking that (fact) into account.” In (1)-(3), it is used to say something that contrasts with a previous statement, while acknowledging that the previous statement is by and large true. In (4) and (5), it is used to introduce a new topic, after expressing provisional agreement with what has been said up to that point. In the latter case, it often expresses the feelings of the speaker at that time.

【たいした】

1. たいしたNだ

（1）たいした人物 だ。たった一人 で今 の事業 をおこしたのだから。／He’s an amazing person. He created this business single-handedly.

（2）中国語 を1年 習 っただけであれだけ話 せるんだから、たいしたものだ。／It’s really something that she can speak Chinese so fluently after studying it for only a year.

（3）あんなに大勢 のお客 さんに一人 でフルコースの料理 を作 るなんて、たいした腕前 だ。／For one person to be able to prepare full-course meals for so many customers is an amazing skill.

（4）A:あの人 、紹介状 も持 たずに社長 に会 いに行 ったそうよ。／I heard he went to see the company president without even taking a letter of invitation.

B:たいした度胸 ね。／That takes a lot of nerve, doesn’t it.

Means that someone’s activities or achievements are remarkable. The N slot is filled by nouns such as もの (thing), 人 (person), 人物 (person, man/woman), 腕前 (skill), 度胸 (courage, nerve), 力量 (capacity).

2. たいしたNではない

（1）たいしたものではありませんが、おみやげにと思 って買 ってきました。／It’s nothing special, but I bought it with the idea it might do as a souvenir.

（2）私 にとってボーナスが多 いか少 ないかはたいした問題 ではない。休 みが取 れるかどうかが問題 だ。／For me, whether or not I get a big bonus is not important. My concern is whether or not I can take time off.

（3）A:朝 から病院 って、なにか大 変 なことがあったんですか。／You said you were at the hospital this morning? Was it anything serious?

B:いや、たいしたことではありません。家 のねこがちょっとけがをしただけです。／No, it’s nothing serious. My cat was slightly injured, that’s all.

Means that something is not very important or serious.

3. たいしたことはない

（1）A:お宅 の奥 さん、料理 がお上手 だそうですね。／I hear that your wife is a good cook.

B:いや、たいしたことはありませんよ。／No, not that good.

（2）A:日本語 、うまいですね。／Your Japanese is very good.

B:いや、たいしたことはありません。敬語 の使 い方 なんか、まだまだです。／No, it’s not that good. I still struggle with using honorific language and things like that.

（3）A:かぜの具合 いはいかがですか。／How is your cold?

B:おかげさまで、たいしたことはありません。／Thank you for your concern. It’s not that bad.

Used to deny the extent of something, with the sense of それほど...ではない (not that much). In (1) and (2), it is used as a response to a compliment and conveys a feeling of modesty.

【だいたい】

（1）大体 のことは伝 えておきます。／I will convey the main points.

（2）だいたいわかりました。／I understand, more or less.

（3）この本 をひとりで日本語 に翻訳 するのはだいたい無理 な話 だ。／It’s almost impossible for one person to translate this book into Japanese.

（4）こんな時間 に電話 するなんてだいたい非常識 な人 だ。／Calling people at such an hour shows that he has practically no common sense.

（5）A:あの子 、いつも忘 れものをするらしいの。／Apparently he always forgets to take something (to school).

B:だいたいね、注意 してやらない君 が悪 いんだよ。／You’re the one to blame, because you never remind him.

（6）だいたいぼくよりあいつの方 が給料 がいいなんて変 だよ。／To begin with, the fact that his salary is higher than mine is just crazy.

（7）A:すみません、遅 れまして。／I’m sorry to be late.

B:だいたいだね、君 は今 まで時間 通 りに来 たことがない。／The thing is, you’ve never arrived on time.

Means “mostly; the greater part” in examples (1) and (2). Can be used to convey a sense of reproach or criticism when the speaker is stating a judgment about something that is 無理 (impossible) or 非常識 (thoughtless), as in (3) and (4). May also be used to preface criticisms, grievances, or complaints against another person, as in (5), (6), and (7).

【たとえ】

（1）たとえその事実 を知 っていたところで、私 の気持 ちは変 わらなかっただろう。／Even if I’d known the truth, my feelings wouldn’t have changed.

（2）たとえ子 どもでもやったことの責任 はとらなくてはいけない。／Even a child has to take responsibility for what he or she has done.

（3）たとえどんなところに住 もうとも、家族 がいればいい。／It doesn’t matter where I live, as long as my family is there.

（4）たとえ大金 をつまれたとしてもそんな仕事 はやりたくない。／I wouldn’t want to do a job like that for all the money in the world.

Means “even supposing that, even if....” たとえ is followed by expressions of concession, such as ても, とも, たところで and としても. 住もうとも in (3) is the written language equivalent of 住んだとしても.

【たとえば】

（1）飲物 でしたら、たとえばコーヒー、紅茶 、ジュースなどを用意 してあります。／For beverages, we have coffee, tea, soft drinks, and so on.

（2）日本語 の中 には、たとえばパン、ドア、ラジオなどたくさんの外来語 が入 っている。／In Japanese, there are many loan words, such as pan (bread), doa (door), rajio (radio), and so on.

（3）ゆっくり過 ごすとしたら、たとえば温泉 なんかどうですか。／If you want to spend some time relaxing, how about a hot spring or something?

（4）A:このごろ運動 不足 なんだ。だけどスポーツするひまもないし金 もないし。／I haven’t been getting enough exercise lately. But I have no time to play sports, and no money either.

B:わざわざ出 かけなくても、たとえばバスをやめて、駅 まで歩 くとかいろいろあるでしょ。／Even if you don’t make a special effort to go somewhere, you can do all sorts of things, like stop using the bus and start walking to the train station.

（5）たとえばこの方程式 のXを2とすると、Yは5になる。／Supposing that X in this equation is 2, then Y will be 5.

（6）たとえば今 ここに1億円 あるとしたら、何 に使 いたい？／Say that there’s a hundred million yen here, right now. What would you want to use it for?

（7）たとえば地球上 に飲 み水 がだんだんなくなっていくとしますね。そういう場合 どうするか。海水 の淡水化 ということが当然 考 えられるでしょう。／Suppose that all the drinking water were gradually disappearing from the earth. What would we do in that case? Desalinating sea water would naturally be one thing to consider.

Used to give a concrete example of something introduced previously. When the example is hypothetical, as in (5) and (6), たとえば is followed by an expression such as とすると or としたら.

【たらどうか】

［V-たらどうか］

（1）別 の方法 で実験 してみたらどうでしょうか。／How about experimenting with a different method?

（2）少 しお酒 でも飲 んでみたらいかがですか。気分 がよくなりますよ。／Why don’t you take a little something—even alcohol? You’ll feel better.

（3）遊 んでばかりいないで、たまには勉強 したらどう？／Instead of playing all the time, how about studying occasionally?

（4）さっさと白状 したらどうなんだ。／Now, come on—let's fess up!

（5）アメリカに留学 してみたらどうかと先生 に勧 められた。／I was encouraged by my teacher to consider study abroad in the U.S.

（6）A:吉田 君 、パーティーには出席 しないって。／Yoshida-kun said that he won’t join the party.

B:もう一度 誘 ってみたら？／Why don’t you invite him again?

Idiomatic expression used in a proposal or a recommendation. Oten used in the form V-てみたらどうか. Has almost the same meaning as てはどうか, but たらどうか is more colloquial. In colloquial language, たらどうなの／どうかしら is used by women, たらどうなんだ is used by men, and たらどう is used by both men and women. However, in formal situations, たらいかがですか／いかがでしょうか is used.

(3) and (4) are examples of when the listener simply won’t follow the speaker’s warning or recommendation; they imply the speaker’s irritation. The latter half of (6) is abbreviated and pronounced with a rising tone.

【ちがいない】

［N／Na　 （である）にちがいない］

［A／V　にちがいない］

（1）あんなすばらしい車 に乗 っているのだから、田村 さんは金持 ちにちがいない。／Tamura-san must be very rich to be driving such a splendid car.

（2）あそこにかかっている絵 は素晴 らしい。値段 も高 いにちがいない。／The picture hanging there is outstanding. It must also have had a high price.

（3）学生 のゆううつそうな様子 からすると、試験 はむずかしかったにちがいない。／Judging from the students’ depressed looks, the exam must have been difficult.

（4）あの人 の幸 せそうな顔 をごらんなさい。きっといい知 らせだったにちがいありません。／Look at that guy’s happy face. It must have been good news.

（5）あの人 は規則 をわざと破 るような人 ではない。きっと知 らなかったにちがいない。／He’s not someone who would break rules deliberately. He must have not known.

（6）A:この足跡 は？／What’s this footprint?

B:あの男 のものだ。犯人 はあいつに違 いない。／It’s that man’s. He must be the culprit.

Expresses that, based on some sort of evidence, the speaker is certain about a matter. The degree of the speaker’s certainty about or possession of an idea is higher than when using だろう. This is frequently used in written language, but it tends to sound exaggerated; thus, with the exception of circumstances like (6), expressions such as きっと...と思います are used instead.

【ちっとも...ない】

（1）この前 の旅行 はちっとも楽 しくなかった。／The last trip was not fun at all.

（2）日本語 がちっとも上達 しない。／My Japanese hasn’t improved one bit.

（3）A:ごめんね。／I’m sorry.

B:いや、いや。ちっともかまわないよ。／No, no, it’s not a problem at all.

（4）妻 が髪形 を変 えたのに、夫 はちっとも気 がつかなかった。／His wife changed her hairstyle, but the husband didn’t notice it at all.

（5）久 しぶりに帰国 した友達 のためにたくさんごちそうを作 ったのに、疲 れていると言 ってちっとも食 べてくれなかった。／I cooked a lot for my friend who had come home (from abroad) after a long time, but he said he was tired and didn’t eat a bite.

（6）ダイビングはこわいものと思 っていたが、やってみたら、ちっともこわくなかった。／I thought scuba diving was a scary thing, but when I tried it, it wasn’t the least bit scary.

Means すこしも/ぜんぜん...ない, and is used to strengthen negativity. It is used in spoken language and is more informal than すこしも. Unlike ぜんぜん, it is not used to express frequency.

（×）ちっとも行ったことがない。／I’ve never been at all.

（○）ぜんぜん行ったことがない。／I’ve never been there.

【つまり】

1. つまり〈restatement〉

（1）彼 は、母 の弟 、つまり私 の叔父 である。／He is my mother’s younger brother, namely, my uncle.

（2）両親 は、終戦 の翌年 、つまり1946 年 に結婚 した。／My parents married the year after the end of the war, that is, in 1946.

（3）相思相愛 の仲 とは、つまりお互 いのことを心底 愛 し合 っている関係 のことである。／“Mutual loving relationship” means a relationship of deep love for each other.

（4）A:この件 については、ちょっと考 えさせてください。／Please let me think about this matter a little.

B:つまり「引 き受 けていただけない」ということですね。／So you can’t agree to do it, is that it?

Used for replacing a phrase or sentence by a different expression that has the same meaning. For example, in (4), following the listener’s statement, the speaker is replacing it using his own words. While close to すなわち, つまり is more like spoken language. Hence in conversation, like example (4), replacing it with すなわち would be unnatural.

2. つまり（は）〈conclusion〉

（1）つまり、責任 は自分 にはないとおっしゃりたいのですね。／Thus, what you want to say is that you have no responsibility for this.

（2）子供 の教育 は、つまりは、家庭 でのしつけの問題 だ。／Children’s education is ultimately a question of discipline at home.

（3）A:まあ、それほど忙 しいというわけでもないんですけど…。／Well, it isn’t that I’m that busy, but....

B:つまり、君 は何 が言 いたいんだ。／So what is it that you want to say?

（4）私 の言 いたいことは、つまり、この問題 の責任 は経営者 側 にあって…。そのつまり、社員 はその犠牲者 だということです。／What I want to say is that the responsibility for this problem is on the side of the management, and that in essence means the employees are the victims.

Used when describing a final conclusion without going into an explanation of the development leading to it. In (1) and (3), it is used to confirm or facilitate the listener’s conclusion. Can also be used in the form つまりは. In (4), つまり is used in spoken language conjunctively. Often replaced by 結局 or 要するに.

【てある】

［V-てある］

（1）テーブルの上 には花 が飾 ってある。／Flowers have been arranged on the tabletops.

（2）A:辞書 どこ？／Where is the dictionary?

B:辞書 なら机 の上 においてあるだろ。／The dictionary? It should be on the desk.

（3）黒板 に英語 でGoodbye！と書 いてあった。／It said “Good-bye” in English on the blackboard.

（4）窓 が開 けてあるのは空気 を入 れかえるためだ。／The window’s been left open to air out the room.

（5）あしたの授業 の予習 はしてあるが、持 っていくものはまだ確 かめていない。／I have prepped for tomorrow’s class, but I haven’t checked what I have to take.

（6）起 きてみると、もう朝食 が作 ってあった。／Breakfast had already been cooked when I got up.

（7）推薦状 は準備 してあるから、いつでも好 きなときにとりにきてください。／The letter of recommendation is ready, so please come anytime to get it.

（8）電車 の中 に忘 れたかさは、事務所 に届 けてあった。／The umbrella which I left on the train had been delivered to the business office.

（9）ホテルの手配 は、もうしてあるので心配 ありません。／The hotel’s already been reserved, so there’s no worry.

（10）パスポートはとってあったので、安心 していたら、ビザも必要 だということが分 かった。／Because I had already gotten a passport, I felt relieved, but then I found out that I needed a visa, too.

（11）その手紙 は、カウンターにおかれてあった。／The letter was lying on the counter.

Uses a transitive verb to express that a situation exists as a result of someone’s action. In some cases, depending on the context, it can have the meaning “do something in preparation for the future.”

In this pattern, the semantic object of the verb becomes the subject and the person who has taken the action is often not expressed, but the existence of that person is implied. There is an expression 窓があいている, similar to 窓があけてある, but the former doesn’t imply an agent. In あけてある, the existence of the agent is felt even though it is not expressed, while this is not felt in あいている. In addition, when the passive is used, as in (11), the existence of the agent is felt more strongly. Refer to【ておく】for the difference between てある and ておく.

【ておく】

［V-ておく］

（1）このワインは冷 たい方 がいいから、飲 むときまで冷蔵庫 に入 れておこう。／This wine is better chilled, so let’s keep it in the fridge until we’re ready to drink it.

（2）帰 るとき窓 は開 けておいてください。／Please leave the window open when you leave.

（3）その書類 はあとで見 ますから、そこに置 いておいて下 さい。／I’ll look at the document later, so please leave it there.

（4）A:岡田 教授 にお目 にかかりたいんですが。／I would like to see Professor Okada.

B:じゃあ、電話 しておくよ。向 こうの都合 がつけば、来週 にでも会 えると思 うよ。／Then I’ll call her. If she’s available, I think you can see her as soon as next week.

（5）インドネシアへ行 く前 にインドネシア語 を習 っておくつもりだ。／Before I go to Indonesia, I intend to learn Indonesian.

（6）よし子 が遅 れて来 てもわかるように、伝言板 に地図 を書 いておいた。／So that Yoshiko will know, even if she arrives late, I drew a map on the notice board.

ておく has the meaning of “taking an action and maintaining the situation which has come about as a result of such action.” Depending on the context, it can mean either a temporary measure or preparation for the future. ...てある also expresses preparation for the future. Apart from the structural difference, ...ておく differs from ...てある in that the former expresses that the preparation has to take place while the latter expresses that the preparation has already been done. In spoken language, ...ておく becomes ...とく.

（例）お母さんに話しとくね。／I’ll let Mom know.

（例）ビール冷やしといてね。／Please chill the beer ahead of time.

【てから】

1. V-てから

（1）先 に風呂 に入 ってから食事 にしよう。／Let’s take a bath first and then have dinner.

（2）遊 びに行 くのは仕事 が終 わってからだ。／I go out to have fun after work finishes.

（3）日本 に来 てから経済 の勉強 を始 めた。／I started studying economics after arriving in Japan.

（4）夏休 みになってから一度 も学校 に行 っていない。／I haven’t been to school even once since summer vacation started.

（5）今 は昼休 みですので、1時 になってから来 て下 さい。／It’s the lunch break now, so please come after one o’clock.

Expresses that X is done before Y. In (1), for example, it expresses the time sequence where 風呂に入る is done before 食事をする.

2. V-てからでないと

a. V-てからでないとV-ない

（1）A:いっしょに帰 ろうよ。／Let’s go back together.

B:この仕事 が終 わってからでないと帰 れないんだ。／I can’t leave until I finish this job.

（2）わが社 では、社長 の許可 をもらってからでなければ何 もできない。／In our company, we can’t do anything unless we first get permission from the president.

（3）まずボタンを押 して、次 にレバーを引 いて下 さい。ボタンを押 してからでなければ、レバーはうごきません。／Please push the button first, then pull the lever. The lever won’t move unless you push the button.

Patterns such as Xてからでないと／なければ／なかったらY express a condition X which has to be fulfilled in order to realize something Y. This means that Y can only be done after X is done. In some cases, expressions of time are used with it, as in the following examples.

（例）3日からでないとその仕事にはかかれない。／I can’t start the job unless it’s from the 3rd.

（例）1時からでなければ会議に出席できない。／I can’t attend the meeting unless it starts at one o’clock.

b. V-てからでないとV-る

（1）A:あした、うちへ泊 まりにおいでよ。／Come and stay over at my house tomorrow.

B:後 で返事 するよ。お母 さんに聞 いてからでないとおこられるから。／I’ll let you know later. If I don’t ask my mother first, she’ll get angry with me.

（2）きちんと確 かめてからでないと失敗 するよ。／You will fail if you don’t check it properly first.

Patterns such as Xてからでないと／なければ／なかったら Y express that “if X is not done, then Y will happen.” Situation Y is usually something negative.

3. V-てからというもの（は）

（1）彼女 は、学生 時代 には、なんとなくたよりない感 じだったが、就職 してからというもの見違 えるようにしっかりした女性 になった。／She gave the feeling of being unreliable in her student days, but now it’s hard to recognize her as the very dependable woman she’s become since she started working.

（2）彼 は、その人 に出会 ってからというもの、人 が変 わったようにまじめになった。／Ever since he met that person, he has become very serious, as if his personality changed.

（3）70 才 を過 ぎても元気 だったのに、去年 つれあいをなくしてからというものは、別人 のようになってしまった。／Here he was hale and hearty even after seventy, but after losing his better half last year, he’s become like a different person.

Means “triggered by an incident.” Used when expressing that a substantial change has taken place since such an incident. Has the feel of written language.

【てくれ】

1. V-てくれ

（1）もう帰 ってくれ。／Just leave, will you?

（2）いいかげんにしてくれ。／Quit that right now!

（3）人前 でそんなこと言 うのはやめてくれよ。／Stop saying such things in front of other people.

（4）こんなものは、どこかに捨 ててきてくれ。／Just throw these things away somewhere.

This is a strong expression which is used to order someone to do an action for the speaker or someone associated with the speaker. Used when speaking to someone equal or junior. Women seldom use this expression.

2. V-ないでくれ

（1）冗談 は言 わないでくれよ。／Are you kidding me?

（2）ここではたばこを吸 わないでください。／Please don’t smoke here.

（3）見 ないで！／Don’t look!

（4）このことは絶対 に外 にはもらさないでいただけませんか。／Can I ask that you never let any of this matter out to anyone else?

Used in patterns such as V-ないでくれ, V-ないでもらえないか, and V-ないでください to request someone not to do the action indicated by V. Constructed by changing the V-て part of the V-てくれ form to a negative te-form.

Used in informal spoken language. Sometimes the latter half of the sentence is omitted, as in example (3). V-ないでください（ませんか）／いただけませんか／いただけないでしょうか are the polite forms of the same expression. V-ないでほしい is also used.

【では2】

Essentially a written form that is used in fairly formal situations. In casual spoken language, じゃ（あ） is used.

1. では〈inference〉

（1）A:私 は 1974 年 の卒業 です。／I graduated in 1974.

B:では、私 は2年 後輩 になります。／Then I must be two years your junior.

（2）A:この1週間毎 晩 帰宅 は 12時 過 ぎだよ。／I’ve been getting home after midnight every night this week.

B:では、睡眠 不足 でしょう。／Then you’re probably short of sleep.

（3）A:彼 、日本語 を 10 年 も習 っているんですよ。／He has been studying Japanese for some ten years.

B:では、日常 の会話 に困 ることはないですね。／Then he probably doesn’t have any trouble with everyday conversation, does he?

（4）A:緊急 の会議 が入 ってしまいまして…／I’ve just had an urgent meeting added to my schedule...

B:では、今日 のパーティにはおいでになれませんね。／Oh, then you won’t be able to attend the party today, will you.

（5）家 を出 たときには、あの袋 はたしかに手 にもっていた。では、途中 のバスの中 に忘 れたということかな。／I know I had that bag in my hand when I left home. So, I’m guessing this means I left it on the bus.

Used at the beginning of a sentence when the speaker is making an inference, based on a newly-acquired fact or on his/her memory of something, that leads to a conclusion. In situations such as (2)-(4), when the speaker is trying to confirm the accuracy of the inference, では functions as an expression of asking or confirmation. (5) is an example of an inference based on the speaker’s memory. In almost all cases, では can be replaced by それなら, そうしたら, （それ）だったら, （そう）すると, and other such expressions.

2. では〈expression of attitude〉

（1）A:すみません。教科書 を忘 れてしまいました。／I’m sorry, but I’ve forgotten my textbook.

B:では、となりの人 に見 せてもらいなさい。／Then ask the person next to you to let you look at hers.

（2）A:用紙 の記入 、終 わりましたが。／I’ve finished filling in this form.

B:じゃ、3番 の窓口 に出 してください。／Then please submit it at Window No. 3.

（3）A:全員 集合 しました。／Everyone is here.

B:では、そろそろ出発 しましょう。／OK, then it’s about time to get going.

（4）A:実 は子供 が病気 なんです。／Actually, I have a sick child at home.

B:では、今日 は帰 ってもいいです。／In that case, you may go home for today.

Appears in sentence-initial position and is used as a chance for the speaker to express an attitude arising from newly-acquired information. Followed by expressions of command, request, intention, permission, and so on. Although this では can be replaced with それなら, そしたら, and （そう）だったら, it cannot be replaced with（そう）すると.

3. では〈shift〉

（1）では、次 の議題 に入 りましょう。／Well then, let’s move on to the next item on the agenda.

（2）では、始 めましょう。／Well then, let’s begin.

（3）では、今日 の授業 はこれで終 わりにします。／Well then, that’s all for today’s class.

（4）では、また明日 。さようなら。／All right then, see you tomorrow. Goodbye.

Placed in sentence-initial position and used as a cue to shift focus to a new topic or situation. Followed by expressions that announce a topic shift or the commencement or conclusion of something. (4) is a formulaic expression used in leave-taking.

【ではあるまいか】

［N／Na 　（なの）ではあるまいか］

［A／V　のではあるまいか］

（1）この話 は全 くの作 り話 なのではあるまいか。／Isn’t this story nothing more than pure fiction?

（2）この品質 で、こんな値段 をつけるとは、あまりにも非常識 ではあるまいか。／Don’t you think it makes no sense to put such a price on something of this quality?

（3）いまどき、彼 のような学生 はめずらしいのではあるまいか。／Wouldn’t you say that a student like him is quite remarkable nowadays?

（4）父 は自分 が癌 だということに気 づいていたのではあるまいか。／Isn’t it most likely that my father realized on his own that he had cancer?

（5）彼 らは私 のことを疑 っているのではあるまいか。／Doesn’t it seem like they have doubts about me?

A more formal way to say ではないだろうか, with the feel of written language. Used in formal writing, such as academic papers or scholarly articles.

→【ではないだろうか】

【てはどうか】

［V-てはどうか］

（1）A:この辺 でちょっと休憩 してはどうですか。／How about taking a break here?

B:そうですね。／That sounds good.

（2）作戦 を変 えてみてはどうですか。／How about changing strategies?

（3）この問題 については、議長 に一任 してはどうだろうか。／What if we leave this matter up to the chairperson?

（4）A:家 の譲渡 のことで家族 の間 でもめているんです。／The family is bickering about the transfer of the house.

B:弁護士 に相談 してみてはどうですか。／Why don’t you consult a lawyer?

（5）A:この壁 はちょっと暗 いですね。壁紙 を取 りかえてみてはどうでしょうか。／Don’t you think this wall is a little dark? How about changing the wallpaper?

B:そうですね。／That could help.

（6）しばらく何 も言 わないでそっとしておいてみては？／How about saying nothing for a while and just letting things be?

An idiomatic expression used to make suggestions or recommendations. Often used in the form V-てみては. Essentially synonymous with V-たらどうか, but V-てはどうか has the tone of written language and is commonly used when writing letters or speaking in formal situations, etc. In ordinary conversation, the V-たらどうか form is preferred. V-ちゃどうか is used in casual conversation. In polite language, forms such as V-てはいかがですか and V-てはいかがでしょうか are used. In (6), the latter half of the expression has been omitted.

【てもいい】

1. V-てもいい〈permission〉

（1）A:入 ってもいいですか。／May I come in?

B:どうぞ。／Please do.

（2）A:すみません、ここに座 ってもいいですか。／Excuse me, may I sit here?

B:あの、連 れがいるんですけど...。／Umm, I’m afraid I have someone with me....

（3）A:この服 、ちょっと着 てみてもいいですか。／May I just try these clothes on?

B:はい、どうぞ。／Yes, go ahead.

（4）あそこは、夕方 八時 から朝六時 までは駐車 してもいいらしい。／Apparently it’s all right to park there from eight in the evening to six in the morning.

（5）A:あしたは何時 に来 ればいいでしょうか。／What time should I come tomorrow?

B:10 時 ぐらいに来 てくれますか。／Could you come at about ten?

A:あの、ちょっと遅 れてもいいですか。／Umm, is it all right if I’m little late?

（6）A:すみませんが、ここで写真 をとってもいいですか。／Excuse me, may I take photos here?

B:申 し訳 ありませんが、ここでは撮影 禁止 になっております。／I’m sorry, but photography is not permitted here.

（7）この部屋 のものは何 でも自由 に使 って（も）いいと言 われました。／I was told we’re free to use anything in this room.

（8）母 は、将来 は、わたしの好 きなようにして（も）いいと言 った。／My mother told me that in the future I can do as I like.

（9）明日 は特 に用 もないから、別 に来 なくてもいいですよ。／There’s nothing in particular for us to do tomorrow, so you don’t have to come.

（10）飲 めないのなら無理 に飲 まなくてもいいよ。／If you can’t drink, then there’s no need to force yourself.

Expresses permission or approval. In conversation, it is used to give permission to or to seek permission from the other person. Also used in the form V-てもよい. Essentially synonymous with V-てもかまわない. Vていい is also used.

When setting the time for an appointment, it is not correct to say 何時に来てもいいですか (What time may I come?). 何時に来たらいいですか or 何時に来ればいいですか should be used instead (What time should I come?).

As shown in (9) and (10), ...なくてもいい means ...する必要がない (it is not necessary to...).

2. V-てもいい〈possibility〉

（1）ワインのかわりに、しょうゆで味 をつけてもいい。／Instead of wine, soy sauce may also be used for flavoring.

（2）そのときすぐ断 ってもよかったのだが、失礼 だと思 ったので、そうしなかったのだ。／I could have refused right then, but I thought it would be impolite, so I didn’t.

（3）滞在 をもう少 し延 ばしてもよかったのだが、切符 がとれたので、予定通 り帰 って来 た。／We could have stayed a little longer, but since we managed to get tickets, we returned home as scheduled.

（4）就職 の時 、東京 の会社 を選 んでもよかったのだが、最終的 には、郷里 に帰 る方 をとったのだ。／When I was looking for a job, I could have chosen a company in Tokyo, but ultimately I chose to return to my hometown.

（5）タクシーで行 ってもよかったのだが、車 で送 ってくれるというので、乗 せてもらった。／I could have gone by taxi, but since she offered me a ride, I took her up on it.

Expresses that there are other alternatives or possibilities. With this meaning, the form ていい is seldom used. When used to refer to the past, the meaning is “there were other choices, but I did not take them.”

3. V-てもいい〈offer〉

（1）A:わたしは、月曜日 はちょっと家 を出 られないんですが。／Monday is not a good day for me to leave the house.

B:じゃあ、わたしがお宅 へ伺 ってもいいですよ。／OK, then I could come to your house.

A:それじゃ、そうしてください。／Then please do.

（2）A:彼 がいないので、この仕事 が進 まないんだ。／He isn’t here, so no progress is being made on this task.

B:ぼくが引 き受 けてもいいよ。／I could take it on.

Used by the speaker to volunteer to do a certain action. Usually used to offer to do something that will benefit the other party.

4. ...てもいい〈concession〉

［N／Na　でもいい］

［A-くてもいい］

（1）印 かんがなければ、サインでもいいですよ。／If you don’t have your seal, then you can just sign it.

（2）給料 がよければ、すこしぐらい危険 な仕事 でもいい。／If the pay is good, then I don’t mind a job with a little risk.

（3）試合 をするのに人数 が足 りないので、へたでもいいですから、誰 か参加者 を探 してください。／There aren’t enough people for the match, so please look for someone else to participate, even if he’s not very good.

（4）多少 不便 でもいいから、自然 環境 のいいところに住 みたいと思 う。／Even if it’s a little inconvenient, I think I want to live somewhere with a good natural environment.

（5）わたしでもよければ、手伝 います。／If I can be of any assistance, I’ll help.

（6）この部署 には若 くてもいいから、しっかりした人 を入 れたい。／We don’t mind putting someone young in this post, provided that he or she is dependable.

（7）手紙 でも、電話 でもいいから、連絡 してみてください。／Either a letter or a telephone call will do—just try to contact him.

This is an expression of concession, indicating that while a compromise may not be the best measure, it will still suffice. When several alternatives are listed, as in (7), it indicates the range of possible choices. Same as ...てもかまわない.

【といっても】

1. といっても

（1）ビデオの作品 を作 った。といっても、せいぜい 10 分 の短 い作品 だが。／I made a video piece. But it was a short piece, no more than ten minutes at most.

（2）新 しいアルバイトが見 つかった。といっても、友達 の代 わりに一週間 働 くだけだ。／I found a new part-time job. That is, I’m just filling in for a friend for a week.

（3）あの人 がこのクラブの会長 です。といっても、大会 であいさつするだけですが。／That’s the president of this club. Which is to say that she just gives the official speeches at tournaments.

（4）仕事場 が変 わりました。といっても、同 じ階 の端 から端 へ移 っただけなんですけど。／I’m working in a new place. But I’ve really just moved from one end of the same floor to the other.

Used to revise an expectation that arises from the previous sentence by indicating that the degree or extent of something is actually not very great. Indicates a limit.

2. ...といっても

a. ...といっても

（1）A:休 みには故郷 へ帰 ります。／I’m going back to my hometown for the vacation.

B:じゃあ、当分 お目 にかかれませんね。／Well then, we won’t be seeing you for a while, will we?

A:いや、帰 るといっても、一週間 程度 で、すぐまた帰 って来 ます。／Actually, even though I’m going home, it’s only for about a week, so I'll be back soon.

（2）料理 ができるといっても、卵焼 きぐらいです。／I say I can cook, albeit just tamagoyaki (Japanese omelet).

（3）シンガポールへ行 ったといっても、実際 は一日 滞在 しただけです。／Although I have been to Singapore, it was really just a one-day stopover.

（4）A:去年 は珍 しく雪 が降 りました。／Last year we had an unusual snowfall.

B:へえ、あんな暖 かい所 でも降 るんですか。／Really? It snows even in such a warm place?

A:いや、降 ったといっても、ほんの少 しで、すぐ消 えてしまいました。／Well, it did snow, but only a little that melted right away.

（5）日本舞踊 ができるといっても、ほんのお遊 び程度 です。／I can do traditional Japanese dance, but it’s just for fun, nothing more.

Used to supplement a previous statement by indicating that the degree or extent of something is actually not very great.

b. ひとくちに...といっても

（1）一口 にアジアといっても、広大 で、多種多様 な文化 があるのです。／The term “Asia” is a simple one, but it refers to a vast area with many diverse cultures.

（2）一口 にバラといっても、実 に豊富 な種類 があります。／What we call “the rose” actually includes an abundant range of varieties.

（3）一口 に日本人 の考 え方 といっても、いろいろな考 え方 があるので、どうとは決 めにくいのです。／Even if you say “the Japanese way of thinking,” it is not easy to determine what this is, because there are many different ways of thinking.

Expresses that something summed up rather simply is actually more complex in nature.

c. ...といっても...ない

（1）A:来週 はテストがあるんです。／I’ve got a test next week.

B:じゃあ、このハイキングはだめですね。／Well, I guess we can’t go hiking then.

A:いえ、テストがあるといっても、そんなにたいしたものじゃありませんから、一日 ぐらいはだいじょうぶです。／No, even though it’s a test, it’s not such a big deal, so taking one day off shouldn’t be a problem.

（2）山登 りが趣味 だと言 っても、そんなに経験 があるわけではありません。／I may say that mountain-climbing is one of my hobbies, but that doesn't mean I have very much experience.

（3）風邪 を引 いたと言 っても、そんなに熱 はない。／I’ve caught some kind of bug, but I don’t have any temperature to speak of.

（4）アルバイトの人 がやめたといっても、店 のほうは別 に支障 はない。／It’s true that a part-time worker has quit, but that won’t cause any problems for the store.

（5）土曜日 には、夫 の姉 が遊 びに来 ることになっている。しかし、お客 が来 るといっても、別 に特 に忙 しいわけではない。／My husband’s sister will be coming to visit us on Saturday. But even though we’ll have a guest, I won’t be particularly busy.

Used to indicate that some kind of special situation has come about, and that although a certain consequence is expected, its degree or extent will not be very great, or no particular problem will arise.

3. ...といってもいいだろう

（1）これは、この作家 の最高 の傑作 だといってもいいだろう。／I think it could be said that this work is the author’s masterpiece.

（2）川田 さんは、かれの本当 の恩師 だといってもいいだろう。／I suppose you could say that Kawada-san is his true mentor.

（3）事実上 の決勝 は、この試合 だと言 ってもいいだろう。／I think it’s possible to say that, for all intents and purposes, this match will be the final.

Means “such-and-such an evaluation is probably not mistaken.” Used when offering an interpretation, judgment, or critique of a situation or person. A more euphemistic expression than ...といえる.

4. ...といってもいいすぎではない

（1）環境破壊 の問題 は、これから世界 の最 も重要 な課題 になるといっても言 い過 ぎではない。／It’s not an overstatement to say that the problem of environmental destruction will be the crucial issue facing the entire world from now on.

（2）成功 はすべて有田 さんのおかげだといってもいいすぎではない。／It’s not too much to say that all our success is thanks to Arita-san.

Means “to say such-and-such is not an exaggeration.” Used for strong emphasis of an assertion. In formal written language, 言いすぎ can be replaced by 過言.

（例）そのニュースは国中の人々を幸福な気分にさせたといっても過言ではない。／It is not an exaggeration to say that this news made people all throughout the nation very happy.

【どうやら】

1. どうやら...そうだ

（1）この分 でいくと、どうやら桜 の開花 は早 まりそうだ。／If it (the weather) continues like this, the cherry blossoms may well bloom early.

（2）むこうから歩 いて来 るのはどうやら田中 さんのようだ。／That looks like Tanaka-san walking toward us from over there.

（3）部屋 から次々 と人 が出 て来 るところをみると、どうやら会議 は終 わったらしい。／Seeing people come out of the room one after the other, it looks like the meeting is over.

Followed by expressions of conjecture such as そうだ, ようだ, or らしい. Indicates uncertainty on the part of the speaker, in the sense that although s/he isn’t absolutely sure, s/he thinks that such an inference is possible.

2. どうやら（こうやら）

（1）急 いだのでどうやら間 に合 った。／We hurried, so somehow or other, we made it on time.

（2）どうやら論文 も完成 に近 づいた。／I’ve somehow managed to come close to finishing my thesis.

（3）どうやらこうやら卒業 することができました。／By hook or by crook, I was able to graduate.

Expresses that, although the outcome is in some way insufficient, a situation or stage of completion that was set as a goal has finally been achieved, as a result of one’s efforts.

【として...ない】

［最小限の数量+として...ない］

（1）戦争 が始 まって以来 、一日 として心 の休 まる日 はない。／Since the war began, I have not had a day’s peace.

（2）期末 試験 では、一人 として満足 のいく答案 を書 いた学生 はなかった。／Not one single student submitted satisfactory answers to the final exam.

（3）高級品 ばかりで、一 つとして私 が買 えそうな品物 は見当 たらない。／There are only luxury goods; I can't find a single thing I can afford to buy.

（4）だれ一人 として、私 の発言 を支持 してくれる人 はいなかった。／There wasn't a single person who supported what I said.

として attaches to words that contain the element 一 (one), which indicates a minimum quantity. Followed by a predicate in the negative form and means “not any, not at all.” Examples of words to which として attaches include 一日 (one day), 一時 (いっとき) (a short time), (だれ) 一人 ((not) one person), and (何) 一つ ((not) a single thing). With question words such as なに (what) and だれ (who), として can be dropped, as below.

（例）だれ一人、私の発言を支持してくれる人はいなかった。／Not one person supported what I said.

More commonly used in written language. In spoken language, expressions like ひとつもない (not a single one) are usually used.

【どちらかというと】

（1）私 はどちらかというと、人前 で発言 するのが苦手 である。／Given the choice, I’d rather not speak up in front of other people.

（2）この店 はどちらかというと若者 向 けで、年配 の客 はあまり見当 たらない。／This store is more for young people, so you won't see many elderly shoppers.

（3）あの教授 はどちらかといえば学者 というよりビジネスマンタイプである。／That professor is more the businessman type than a scholar.

（4）大阪 も悪 くないが、どちらかというと私 は京都 の方 が好 きだ。／Osaka isn’t bad, but on the whole I prefer Kyoto.

（5）最近 の大学生 は、どちらかといえば男子 より女子 のほうがよく勉強 して成績 もよい傾向 がある。／The recent trend for college students is that, generally speaking, the women study harder and get better grades than the men.

Means “on the whole” or “in general.” Used when making an evaluation of the character or special features of people or things. Means that, by and large, a certain characteristic or tendency can be acknowledged. Essentially synonymous with どちらかといえば.

【ともかく】

1. Nはともかく（として）

（1）見 かけはともかく味 はよい。／This may not look good, but it tastes delicious.

（2）学歴 はともかく人柄 にやや難点 がある。／His educational background is fine, but there is a little problem with his personality.

（3）奥 さんはともかくとしてご主人 はとてもいい人 だ。／I can’t say much about the wife, but the husband is a very nice person.

（4）細 かい点 はともかく全体的 に見 れば、うまく行 ったと言 えるのではなかろうか。／Putting aside the details, can we not conclude that on the whole it went very well?

（5）勝敗 はともかくとして、一生懸命 頑張 ろう。／Whether we win or lose, let’s make every effort to do our best.

Nはともかく means “putting aside N (for the moment).” It is used to say that the matter described after ともかく is more important and should be given priority. Nはとにかく(として) can also be used.

2. ともかくV

（1）雨 で中止 になるかもしれないが、ともかく行 ってみよう。／It may get rained out, but let’s go anyway.

（2）ともかく、言 われたことだけはやっておきました。／Anyway, I did what I was told.

（3）ともかく使 ってみないことにはいい製品 かどうかは分 からない。／I can’t tell whether this is a good product or not until I actually use it.

（4）ともかくお医者 さんに見 てもらった方 がよい。／You should go and see a doctor anyway.

Used with verbs that express an intentional act, ともかく means to go ahead and take action, rather than spending time debating the pros and cons of that action. ともかく can be replaced by とにかく.

【なくては】

［N／Na　でなくては］

［A-くなくては］

［V-なくては］

（1）我慢強 い人 でなくては彼女 と付 き合 うのは難 しい。／Unless you have the patience of a saint, it’s hard to get along with her.

（2）どんなにお金 があっても健康 でなくては幸 せだとは言 えない。／No matter how much money you have, if you aren’t in good health, you can’t say you’re happy.

（3）成績 がもっとよくなくてはこの大学 への合格 は無理 だろう。／Without better grades, you probably won’t be able to pass the entrance exam for this university.

（4）彼 がいなくては生 きていけない。／I can’t live without him.

（5）聞 いてみなくては分 からない。／Unless you ask, you’ll never know.

（6）もっと食 べなくては大 きくなれないよ。／You won’t grow up to be big and strong unless you eat more.

Used with the negative form of a verb or a negative expression such as 無理だ (impossible) or 難しい (difficult) at the end of the sentence. Has the meaning “unless X, Y is impossible.” Used when the speaker wants to say that realization of the situation or event expressed in the first clause is desirable or necessary. In many cases, なくては can be replaced by なかったら, なければ and/or ないと. In casual spoken language, N／Naじゃなくちゃ and A-くなくちゃ／V-なくちゃ are used instead.

【なくてはいけない】

［N／Na　でなくてはいけない］

［A-くなくてはいけない］

［V-なくてはいけない］

（1）履歴書 は自筆 のものでなくてはいけない。／Your resume has to be handwritten.

（2）教師 はどの生徒 に対 しても公正 でなくてはならない。／Teachers have to be fair to every single student.

（3）家族 が住 むにはもう少 し広 くなくてはだめだ。／If a family is going to live here, it needs to be a little more spacious.

（4）目上 の人 と話 す時 はことばづかいに気 をつけなくてはいけない。／You must be careful with the way you speak when you speak to a superior.

（5）家族 のために働 かなくてはならない。／I have to work for the sake of my family.

This expression takes the forms V-なくてはいけない／ならない／だめだ and means that generally it is “obligatory” or “necessary” to do a certain action or to be a certain way. In spoken Japanese, なくては may be contracted to なく(っ)ちゃ and the latter part いけない／ならない／だめだ may be omitted, as below.

（例）もっとまじめに勉強しなくちゃだめだよ。／You’ve got to study harder.

（例）もう行かなくちゃ。／I've gotta go now.

Regarding the difference between なくてはいけない and なくてはならない, see なければ (Usage 2).

【なさい】

［R-なさい］

（1）うるさい。すこし静 かにしなさい。／You’re making too much noise! Quiet down a little.

（2）明日 も学校 があるんだから、早 く寝 なさい。／Tomorrow is another school day, so hurry up and go to bed.

（3）A:あいつ、本当 に馬鹿 なんだから。／That guy is a real idiot!

B:よしなさいよ。そんな言 い方 するの。／Cut it out! Don’t talk that way.

（4）A:明日 のパーティー、どうするの？／Are you going to the party tomorrow?

B:行 こうかな。どうしようかな。／Hmm...I wonder. Should I go, or not?

A:迷 ってないで、行 きなさいよ。絶対 おもしろいから。／Don’t think about it too much, just go! I’m sure it’ll be fun.

（5）《試験 の問題 》次 の文 を読 んで、記号 で答 えなさい。／《exam question》Read the following passage and answer the questions, using the symbols.

Indicates a command or instruction. Often used by people in supervisory positions. For instance, parents use it to address children, and teachers to address students. However, なさい can also be used between people with close relationships, such as family or friends, as shown in (3) and (4). (3) is an expression of prohibition used to admonish the addressee regarding his words and actions, and (4) is a strong suggestion. なさい may also be used in the instructions for exam questions, as in (5).

ごめんなさい (I’m sorry) is an expression of apology used between people with a close relationship. おやすみなさい (Good night/Sleep well) is a conventionalized expression used before going to bed.

【なるほど】

（1）いい店 だとは聞 いていたが、なるほどサービスもいいし料理 もうまい。／I’ve heard that this is a good restaurant. Indeed, the service is excellent and the food is really good.

（2）あなたの言 うことはなるほどもっともだが、私 の立場 も考 えてほしい。／It is true that what you are saying is reasonable, but I would like you to consider my position.

（3）なるほど、富士山 というのは美 しい山 だ。／Indeed, Fuji-san (Mount Fuji) is a beautiful mountain.

（4）なるほど、噂 には聞 いていましたが、実際 に使 ってみると本当 に便利 なものなのですね。／I had heard talk about it and—as they said—it really was convenient when I used it.

（5）A:きのうは久 しぶりに大学 時代 の友達 に会 ってきたよ。／Yesterday I saw my friends from my university days after a long while.

B:なるほど。だからあんなに嬉 しそうにしていたんですね。／Oh, so that’s why you looked so happy.

（6）A:このコピー機 は、濃度 調整 が自動 でできるようになっております。／This copier is able to control the boldness of fonts automatically.

B:なるほど。／I see.

A:それから、用紙 の選択 も自動 になっております。／Furthermore, it can also automatically select the paper size.

B:なるほど。／I got it.

Expresses the speaker’s understanding with satisfaction that the speaker agrees with knowledge s/he obtained from others or accepts what the listener is contending. Also used when the speaker reconfirms his/her own information, or when the speaker is convinced by an answer to his/her question. なるほど sounds casual and less formal than 納得, as in (6). There is a use in which the speaker shows the listener that s/he agrees with the listener or s/he is making brief responses while listening to the listener. However, なるほど is not used towards superiors because this use may sound arrogant.

【なんか】

1. なんか〈things〉

A casual way of saying なにか. Used in spoken Japanese.

→【なにか】

a. なんか

（1）A:なんかたべるものない？／Is there anything to eat?

B:冷蔵庫 見 てみたら？　なんか入 っていると思 うけど。／Why don’t you look inside the fridge? I think there should be something.

（2）誕生日 にはなんか買 ってやろうと思 っています。／I’m thinking of buying something for his birthday.

（3）今日 手伝 えなかったことは、きっと何 かで償 うよ。／I’ll surely make up for what I couldn’t do for you today.

（4）何 か変 な音 が聞 こえませんでしたか。／Didn’t you just hear some strange noise?

（5）この部屋 、何 か臭 わない？／Don’t you think this room smells like something?

Expresses something or some state which one cannot clearly refer to.

b. なんか〈appearance〉

（1）彼女 と話 していると、なんかほっとした気持 ちになる。／When I talk to her, I just feel relieved for some reason.

（2）あの人 の言 っていること、なんか変 だと思 いませんか。／Don’t you think what she is saying is somewhat strange?

（3）今日 は子供 たちがなんか妙 に静 かですね。なにかいたずらをしているんじゃありませんか。／The children are unusually quiet today. I wonder if they are up to something naughty.

（4）なんか不思議 だなあ、この町 は。前 に来 たことがあるような気 がしてならない。／I don’t know why, but I feel strange about this town. I can’t help thinking that I’ve been here before.

Expresses the meaning of “I don’t know why it’s so” or “for some reason.”

c. ...かなんか

［N／A／V　かなんか］

（1）今度 の休 みは映画 かなんか行 かない？／Shall we go to a movie or something on the next day off?

（2）この傷 は石 かなんかがぶつかってできたものでしょう。／I guess that a stone or something hit it to create this scrape.

（3）お見舞 いには果物 かなんかを持 って行 くことにしよう。／I’ll take fruit or something when I pay a visit at the hospital.

（4）田中 君 は試験 が近 いかなんかでとても忙 しそうです。／Tanaka-kun seems to be very busy because his exams are approaching or something.

（5）A:田中 君 はどうしたの？／What happened to Tanaka-kun?

B:忘 れものをしたかなんかで、取 りに戻 っています。／He went back because he forgot something, I guess.

Expresses something that one cannot refer to clearly but is similar to the thing mentioned.

d. Nやなんか

（1）スポーツは好 きですが、野球 やなんかの球技 はあまり得意 ではないんですよ。／I like sports, but I’m not good at ball games like baseball.

（2）出張 やなんかで旅行 をするときはいつもこの鞄 を持 っていきます。／I always bring this bag when I do things like make a business trip.

（3）この話 は友達 やなんかには言 わないで下 さいね。／Please don’t tell this story to your friends or anybody else, OK?

（4）山 で遭難 したときは、持 っていたチョコレートやなんかを食 べて救助 を待 ちました。／When I got lost in the mountains, while I was waiting to be saved I ate things like the chocolate that I had brought with me.

Used to express the thing mentioned, N, and some other similar things.

2. なんか

a. Nなんか

（1）お酒 はワインなんか好 きで、よく飲 んでいます。／As for alcohol, I like things like wine and drink it quite often.

（2）食料品 なんかは近 くの店 で買 うことができます。／You can buy groceries and other things at the shop nearby.

（3）山本 さんや鈴木 さんなんかはこの案 に反対 のようです。／People like Yamamoto-san and Suzuki-san seem to be against this idea.

（4）部品 やなんかは揃 っているんですが、技術者 がいないので直 せないんです。／We have all the parts and things, but we can’t fix it because we don’t have a technician.

Exemplifies the main one(s) among various other items. Implies that there are other similar sorts of things. This expression is used in the form など in casual speech.

b. V-たりなんかして

（1）休 みの日 は本 を読 んだりなんかして過 ごします。／I spend my days off doing things like reading books.

（2）どうしたの？　ひとりで笑 ったりなんかして。／What’s the deal? How come you’re snickering by yourself and all?

（3）お父 さんたら急 に怒 り出 したりなんかして。この頃 少 し疲 れてるのかな。／What’s with Father that he does things like suddenly get angry? I wonder if he hasn’t been a little tired out these days.

Exemplifies main one(s) among various other actions. Implies that there are other similar sorts of actions. A colloquial equivalent of など that is used in casual speech.

c. なんか...ない

（1）お金 がないから、旅行 なんか滅多 にできない。／I don’t have any money at all, so I can hardly do things like take a trip.

（2）あんな男 となんか口 もききたくない。／I don’t even want to speak to such a guy.

（3）そんなばかげたことなんか考 えたこともありません。／I’ve never thought about such a stupid thing.

（4）こんな汚 い部屋 になんか一日 だって泊 まりたくない。／I don’t want to stay in such a filthy room even for one night.

（5）こんな天気 の良 い日 に家 の中 で本 を読 んでなんかいないで、外 を散歩 しましょうよ。／Don’t do things like reading a book inside on such a nice day as this. Let’s take a walk outside.

（6）あんな映画 ちっともおもしろくなんかないよ。／That movie is not at all interesting.

With a variety of elements such as a noun, a verb, or a noun + verb, this なんか is followed by some negative expression. Although なんか...ない expresses negation towards a thing/state/event mentioned in the sentence, it also implies at the same time the speaker’s derogatory, humble, or unexpected feeling toward the thing/state/event expressed in the phrase with なんか. なんか...ない is rephrased as など...ない in casual speech.

【なんて2】

1. Nなんて

（1）あなたなんて大嫌 い。／I hate you!

（2）そんな馬鹿 げた話 なんて、だれも信 じませんよ。／Nobody believes such a ridiculous story.

（3）あの人 の言 うことなんて、嘘 に決 まっています。／Everything that person says has got to be a lie!

Topicalizes something that the speaker thinks ridiculous or stupid. A colloquial expression.

2. ...なんて

（1）みんなには時間 を守 れなんて言 ったけど、そう言 った本人 が遅刻 してしまった。／She had told us all to be on time, but the very person who had said it arrived late.

（2）息子 が大学 進学 は嫌 だなんて言 い出 して困 っている。／I’ve been really troubled since my son said he didn’t like the idea of continuing on to a university.

（3）私 が彼 をだましたなんて言 っているらしいけど、彼 のほうこそ嘘 を付 いているんです。／He seems to be saying that I deceived him, but he’s the one who was lying.

（4）あやまれば許 してもらえるなんて甘 い考 えは捨 てなさい。／Forget about your wishful thinking that if you apologize, you are forgiven.

（5）まさか、親 に頼 めば借金 を払 ってもらえるなんて思 っているんじゃないでしょうね。／Surely you’re not thinking that if you ask your parents, they’ll pay your debt.

Followed by a verb such as 言う (say), 思う (think), 考える (think about) or a noun corresponding to one of these verbs. Expresses the speaker’s unexpected or scornful feeling towards what is said in the preceding clause along with the content of the speaker’s utterance and thought. This is a casual way of saying などと．

3. ...なんて

［N／Na　（だ）なんて］

［A／V　なんて］

（1）一家 そろって海外旅行 だなんて、うらやましいですね。／I envy you for being able to travel abroad with all your family.

（2）あなたにそんなことを言 うなんて、実 にひどい男 だ。／What a truly horrible man he is to say such a thing to you!

（3）こんなところであなたに会 うなんて、びっくりしましたよ。／It’s surprising to see you here.

（4）こんな安 い給料 でまじめに働 くなんて馬鹿 らしい。／It’s ridiculous to work hard for this low pay.

（5）あんな怠 け者 が一生懸命 働 きたいなんて、嘘 にきまっているでしょう。／There’s no way such a lazy person like that would want to work hard!

（6）この吹雪 の中 を出 て行 くなんて、命 を捨 てに行 くようなものだ。／Venturing out in this blizzard is like throwing your life away.

Followed by an expression to show the speaker’s evaluation, such as うらやましい (envious) or ひどい (terrible), and indicates the thing/state/event to be evaluated. Often accompanies the speaker’s surprise, unexpectedness, or scornful feeling to consider a thing/person stupid or ridiculous. Used in casual speech.

【にこしたことはない】

［Nであるにこしたことはない］

［Na （である）にこしたことはない］

［A-いにこしたことはない］

［V-るにこしたことはない］

（1）体 はじょうぶにこしたことはない。／Keeping your health is always better.

（2）金 はあるにこしたことはない。／Money is never unnecessary.

（3）そうじのことを考 えないかぎり、家 は広 いにこしたことはない。／As long as you don’t think about cleaning, spacious houses are always better.

（4）なにごとも慎重 にやるにこしたことはないといつも私 に言 っている父 が、きのう階段 から落 ちて足 を折 った。／My father, who had kept saying to me that things should always be done carefully, fell down the stairs and broke his leg.

Expresses the meaning of “...is better.” This expression is often used to indicate something naturally considered as common knowledge.

【にそくして】

［Nにそくして］

（1）事実 にそくして想像 をまじえないで事件 について話 してください。／Based on the facts and without embellishing, please tell me about the incident.

（2）経験 にそくしていうと、ぼくの人生 にとって若 いときの異文化 体験 の意味 はとても大 きい。／Based on past experiences, my encountering different cultures in my youth has had a great significance in my life.

（3）ゼロ才児 保育 につきましてはそれぞれの家庭 で事情 が異 なると思 いますから、実情 に即 して対処 いたします。／I think the care of babies under the age of one differs from family to family, so I will deal with this to meet the needs of the actual circumstances.

（4）この問題 は私的 な感情 ではなく、法 にそくして解釈 しなければならない。／This problem must be solved in accordance with the law and not personal feelings.

（5）法律 に則 して言 うと、今回 の事件 は刑事事件 として取 り扱 うべき性格 のものだ。／Based on the law, this incident is characteristic of a criminal case and should be treated accordingly.

With a noun expressing a fact, experience, or a norm, にそくして expresses the meaning of “along something,” “following something” or “based on something.” When にそくして is preceded by a noun expressing a fact or experience, 即して is used as shown in (1)-(3), whereas when it is preceded by a noun expressing a law or a norm, 則して is used as shown in (4) and (5).

【にはおよばない】

1. ...にはおよばない

［Nにはおよばない］

［V-るにはおよばない］

（1）検査 では何 も異常 は見 つかりませんでした。すっかり元気 になりましたから、ご心配 には及 びません。／Nothing abnormal was found in the examination. I’m completely recovered, so you don’t need to worry.

（2）分 かりきったことだから、わざわざ説明 するには及 ばない。／This is an obvious matter, so you don’t need to explain.

（3）こんな遠 くまで、はるばるお越 しいただくには及 びません。／Please do not bother to come all the way to such a distant place.

Expresses the meaning of “it is not necessary to do something” or “there is no need to do something.” Can be rephrased as ...にはあたらない.

2. それにはおよばない

（1）A:車 で家 までお送 りしましょう。／Let me drive you home.

B:いいえ、それには及 びません。歩 いても5分 ほどの所 ですから、どうぞご心配 なく。／No, please don’t bother. It takes me only five minutes or so on foot, so don’t worry.

（2）A:空港 までお迎 えにあがりますよ。／I’ll pick you up at the airport.

B:大丈夫 です。よく知 っている所 ですから、それには及 びませんよ。／I’ll be fine. I know the place well, so please don’t bother.

Used to decline an offer made by the listener and means “you don’t need to go to such an extent.” Implies the speaker’s acknowledgement of the listener’s consideration, and sounds more formal than その必要はありません.

【の1】

1. NのN

a. NのN〈affiliation〉

（1）これはあなたの財布 じゃないですか。／Isn’t this your wallet?

（2）こちらは東京 電気 の田中 さんです。／This is Tanaka-san, from the Tokyo Electric Company.

（3）東京 のアパートはとても高 い。／Apartments in Tokyo are very expensive.

The first noun modifies the noun that comes after it and expresses the owner, affiliation, location, etc. of the thing indicated by the second noun.

b. NのN〈characteristic〉

（1）病気 の人 を見舞 う。／(I) visit the patient.

（2）バラの花 を贈 る。／(I) give roses.

（3）3時 の電車 に乗 る。／(I) take the three o’clock train.

（4）カップ1杯 の水 を加 える。／(I) add a cup of water.

The first noun modifies the noun that comes after it and expresses a variety of meanings, such as a characteristic, the state, the kind, or the quantity of the noun.

c. NのN〈apposition〉

（1）友人 の和男 に相談 した。／I consulted my friend, Kazuo.

（2）社長 の木村 さんをご紹介 しましょう。／Let me introduce you to Kimura-san, the company president.

（3）これは次女 の安子 でございます。／This is my second daughter, Yasuko.

Expresses that the N preceding の and the N following it are the same person/thing. The second noun slot is often filled by a proper noun, such as the name of someone or something.

d. N（+助 詞 ）のN

（1）子供 の成長 は早 い。／Children grow up fast.

（2）自転車 の修理 を頼 んだ。／(I) requested bicycle repairs.

（3）アメリカからの観光客 を案内 する。／(I) guide tourists from the United States.

（4）京都 までのバスに乗 った。／(I) took the bus that goes to Kyoto.

（5）田中 さんとの旅行 は楽 しかった。／The trip with Tanaka-san was fun.

（6）京都 での宿泊 はホテルより旅館 のほうがいい。／If you stay in Kyoto, you should try a Japanese-style inn rather than a hotel.

Expresses the relationship between two nouns: 子供 and 成長 in 子供が成長する (children grow up), 自転車 and 修理 in 自転車を修理する (repair the bicycle), アメリカ and 観光客 in アメリカから観光客が来る (tourists come from the United States). The first noun modifies the second. When the particles が and を are used in the kernel (basic) clauses, as in 子供が成長する and 自転車を修理する, these particles do not appear in the NのN phrases, which in this case are 子供の成長 (children’s growth) and 自転車の修理 (bicycle repairs). Other types of particles, however, must be retained, as in アメリカからの観光客 (tourists from the United States) and 田中さんとの旅行 (the trip with Tanaka-san). The particle に does not appear in this pattern at all. へ is used instead of に, as in the example below.

（×）母にの手紙／a letter to for my mother

（○）母への手紙／a letter to my mother

e. Nの...N

（1）彼 の書 いた絵 はすばらしい。／The picture he drew is marvelous.

（2）学生 たちの歌 う声 が聞 こえる。／I can hear the students singing.

（3）タイプの上手 な人 を探 している。／I am looking for a person who is good at typing.

（4）花 の咲 く頃 にまた来 てください。／Please come to visit us again when flowers are in bloom.

In this pattern, の is used instead of が in a clause that modifies a noun. For example, the clauses 彼が書いた絵 (the picture he drew) and タイプが上手な人 (a person who is good at typing), which modify the nouns 絵 (picture) and 人 (person), respectively, become 彼の書いた絵 and タイプの上手な人.

2. ...の

a. Nの

（1）これは私 のです。／This is mine.

（2）電気 製品 はこの会社 のが使 いやすい。／Regarding electric products, the ones from this company are easy to use.

（3）この電話 は壊 れてますので、隣 の部屋 のをお使 い下 さい。／This phone is out of order, so please use the one in the next room.

（4）ラーメンなら、駅前 のそば屋 のが安 くておいしいよ。／When it comes to Chinese noodles, those in the noodle shop by the station are delicious and inexpensive.

（5）柄物 のハンカチしか置 いてないけど、無地 のはありませんか。／I can find only handkerchiefs with a pattern...do you have any plain ones?

Means “something from/in (that belongs to/that has) N.”

b. ...の

［Na なの］

［A／V　の］

（1）これはちょっと小 さすぎます。もう少 し大 きいのはないですか。／This is a little too small. Do you have one that’s a little larger?

（2）みんなで料理 を持 ちよってパーティーをしたんだけど、私 が作 ったのが一番 評判 よかったんだ。／We had a potluck party where everyone brought a dish, and the one I made was the most popular.

（3）これは大 きすぎて使 いにくい。もっと小 さくて便利 なのを探 さなくてはならない。／This one is hard to use because it’s too big. I have to look for something smaller and handier.

（4）その牛乳 は古 いから、さっき買 ってきたのを使 って下 さい。／That milk is old, so please use the one that I’ve just bought.

Placed after a verb or an adjective and means “something large,” “something I made,” etc.

c. Nの...の

［Nの Na なの］

［Nの　A／V　の］

（1）戸棚 のなるべく頑丈 なのを探 してきてほしい。／I want you to go out and find a cabinet that’s as sturdy as possible.

（2）ビールの冷 えたのはないですか。／Is there any beer that’s been chilled?

（3）袋 の中 にリンゴの腐 ったのが入 っていた。／There was a rotten apple in the bag.

Used to talk about the thing denoted by N, referring in particular to a restricted class of things that are in the state expressed by the modifying clause. For instance, (2) literally means “with regard to beer, the ones (bottles/cans) that have been chilled.”

【のは...だ】

［N／Na　なのは...だ］

［A／V　のは...だ］

Used in the pattern XのはYだ. X states something that the listener already knows or can expect, and Y expresses something new and previously unknown to the listener.

1. ...のは　Nだ／N+助 詞 +だ

（1）このことを私 に教 えてくれたのは山田 さんです。／The person who told me this is Yamada-san.

（2）彼 の言 うことを信 じているのはあなただけだ。／You’re the only one who believes what he says.

（3）ここに通 うようになったのは去年 の3月 からです。／It was March of last year when I started to come here.

Used to describe a certain situation and then indicate a person, thing, etc. relevant to the realization of that situation. だ／です is preceded by either a noun or a noun/particle combination. However, the particles が and を cannot be used.

（×）このことを私に教えてくれたのは山田さんがです。／The person who told me this is Yamada-san.

2. のは...からだ

（1）彼女 が試験 に失敗 したのは、体 の調子 が悪 かったからだ。／The reason she failed the exam was that she didn’t feel well.

（2）大阪 に行 ったのは事故 の原因 をたしかめたかったからです。／The reason I went to Osaka was that I wanted to determine the cause of the accident.

Used to express a certain situation or event and then state the cause or reason for it.

3. のは...ためだ

（1）電車 が遅 れたのは、踏切 事故 があったためだ。／The reason the train was late was that there was an accident at a railroad crossing.

（2）彼 らが国 に帰 ったのは、子供 たちに会 うためだ。／The reason they went back to their country was so they could see their children.

Used to express a certain situation or event and then state the cause or reason for it.

4. のは...おかげだ

（1）子供 が助 かったのはあなたのおかげです。／It is thanks to you that my child was saved.

（2）この事業 が成功 したのは、みんなが力 を合 わせて頑張 ったおかげだ。／We owe the success of this project to your teamwork and effort.

Used to express a favorable situation or event and then state what caused it.

5. のは...せいだ

（1）雪崩 に巻 き込 まれたのは、無謀 な計画 のせいだ。／The reason we got caught in an avalanche was that our plan was reckless.

（2）試合 に負 けたのは私 がミスをしたせいだ。／We lost the game because I made an error.

Used to express an unfavorable situation or event and then state what caused it.

【はい】

Used to express an affirmative answer, a back-channel response (see below), and so on. うん and ええ are similar to はい. However, うん is used only in informal situations with family members, friends, or other people who have a close relationship to the speaker, or towards people of lower status than the speaker. In formal situations, はい or ええ is used. To express a negative answer, いいえ, ううん, and いや are used.

1. はい〈affirmation〉

（1）A:これはあなたの本 ですか。／Is this your book?

B:はい、そうです。／Yes, it is.

（2）A:明日 、学校 へいきますか。／Are you going to school tomorrow?

B:はい、行 きます。／Yes, I am.

（3）A:おいしいですか。／Is it good?

B:はい、とてもおいしいです。／Yes, it’s really delicious.

（4）A:便利 ですか。／Is it convenient?

B:はい、便利 です。／Yes, it is convenient.

（5）A:国 へ帰 るんですか。／So, are you going back to your country?

B:はい、そうです。／Yes, I am.

Used in reply to a question the speaker has asked to confirm whether or not a judgment s/he has made is correct. Means that the speaker’s judgment is, in fact, correct. In this case, はい、そうです can be used only in response to a question about a noun, as exemplified in (1).

When responding to a question with a verb or an adjective, the same verb or adjective must be repeated, as shown in (2), (3) and (4). However, if the question form is のですか or んですか, as in (5), then はい、そうです can be used.

（例）A:これは、あなたの車ではありませんね。／This isn’t your car, is it?

B1: はい、ちがいます。／That’s right, it isn’t.

B2: いいえ、わたしのです。／Actually (= that’s wrong), it is mine.

With a negative question like the one in the example above, はい is used when the speaker’s judgment is correct, and いいえ is used when his/her judgment is incorrect. Thus, if the judgment “this is not your car” is correct, the response should be はい, as in B1’s response はい、違います (That’s right, it isn’t) or はい、私の車ではありません (That’s right, it’s not my car).

As can be seen in the examples above, the answer to a negative question is はい when the expectation or judgment of the person asking the question is correct, and いいえ when it is not. In other words, the answer is not determined by whether the judgment itself is affirmative or negative. In actual conversation, answering a negative question without はい or いいえ is also common.

2. はい〈consent〉

（1）A:行 ってくれますね。／You’ll go for me, won’t you?

B:はい。／Yes.

（2）A:いっしょにやりましょう。／Let’s do it together.

B:はい。／Yes, let’s.

（3）A:これをあっちに持 って行 ってください。／Please take this over there.

B:はい、わかりました。／All right, I will.

（4）A:いっしょに食事 をしませんか。／Shall we have dinner together?

B1: はい、行 きましょう。／B1: Yes, let’s go.

B2: いや、今日 はちょっと。／B2: Actually, today’s not so good for me....

（5）母 :早 くおふろに入 りなさい。／Mother: Hurry up and get into the bath.

子 :はいはい。／Child: Yes, yes!

母 :「はい」は、一回 ！／Mother: You only need to say “yes” once!

Used to consent to a request, demand, invitation, etc. (4) is in the form of a question, but since it is a request, not an inquiry to confirm whether or not something is correct, consent is indicated by the use of はい. When declining a request, speakers tend not to use いいえ, since it may sound like a rather strong refusal. As shown in (5), repetition of はい in response to a request or demand sounds rather rude, because it gives the impression that the speaker is responding reluctantly.

3. はい〈response〉

（1）A:山田 君 。／Yamada-kun?

B:はい。／Yes.

（2）A:ちょっとおたずねしますが...。／Could I ask you something...?

B:はい。／Yes.

（3）A:あのう。／Excuse me....

B:はい。／Yes?

（4）A:おーい。ちょっと。／Hey, you there.

B:はい。／Yes?

Used by an addressee to respond when someone calls out to him/her, when attendance is being taken, and so on. In this case, ええ cannot be used. In casual situations, the addressee may also respond with はあい, なに, なあに, etc.

4. はい〈back-channel response〉

（1）《電話 で》／《on the phone》

A:来週 の旅行 のことですが...。／About the trip next week....

B:はい。／Yes.

A:他 の方 は皆 さんいらっしゃることになったんですが...。／All the others have decided to go, but....

B:あ、はい。／Oh, really.

A:ええ、それで、Bさんのご都合 はどうかと思 いまして...。／Yes, so I’m wondering whether or not you can go too....

B:すみません。それがですねえ。急 に用事 ができてしまいまして、申 し訳 ないんですが...。／I’m sorry. About that, you know...something has come up all of a sudden. I’m very sorry, but....

A:だめですか...。／So you can’t come....

はい, ええ and うん are often used as “back-channel” responses. These are brief responses that show only that the addressee understands or is listening to what the speaker is saying. They do not mean that the addressee agrees with the speaker.

5. はい〈getting someone’s attention〉

（1）はい、みなさんこっちを向 いて。／Okay, everyone, look over here.

（2）はい、みなさん出発 しますよ。／All right, everyone, we’re leaving now.

（3）はいどうぞ。／Here you are.

（4）はい、お茶 。／Here is your tea.

（5）はい、これでございます。／Here you are, this is it.

Used to attract the addressee’s attention. In this case, うん and ええ cannot be used.

6. はい〈confirmation〉

（1）A:おじいさんは、こちらには長 くお住 まいですか。／Has this been your home for a long time, Grandfather?

B:私 ですか。私 は、戦前 からずっとここに住 んでおります。はい。／Me? I’ve been living here since before the war. Yes.

（2）客 :どっちが似合 うかしら。／Customer: I wonder which one looks best on me.

店員 : そりゃもう、どちらもお似合 いでございます。はい。／Salesperson: Well, I would say that both of them suit you. Yes, indeed.

When a speaker adds はい to the end of one of his/her own statements or remarks, it sounds like s/he is confirming what s/he has just said. Sounds old-fashioned or humble.

【はおろか】

［Nはおろか］

（1）私 は、海外旅行 はおろか国内 旅行 さえ、ほとんど行 ったことがない。／I’ve hardly ever traveled in this country, much less abroad.

（2）吉井 さんはアレルギーがひどくて、卵 はおろかパンも食 べられないそうだ。／Since Yoshii-san has terrible allergies, she can’t even eat bread, let alone eggs.

（3）この学生 には単位 は出 せません。今学期 はレポートはおろか出席 さえしていないんです。／I can’t give this student credit for this course. Not only has he never turned in a paper, he’s never even been to class.

（4）発見 されたとき、その男 の人 は住所 はおろか名前 すら記憶 していなかったという。／I heard that when that man was found, he couldn’t even remember his name, let alone his address.

（5）もし歩 いていてピストルを突 きつけられたら絶対 に逆 らわないでお金 を渡 しなさい。さもないと金 はおろか命 までなくすことになるよ。／If someone points a gun at you on the street, you must give up your money without resisting. Otherwise, you will lose not only your money but also your life.

（6）戦争 も末期 になると、青年 はおろか妻子 ある中年 の男 まで戦場 に送 り込 まれた。／Towards the end of the war, not only young men but also middle-aged men with wives and children were sent to the front.

Often used with a negative expression, in the pattern XはおろかYさえ／も／すら...ない. Means that something is a matter of course or goes without saying. Used to emphasize Y by first presenting X, which has a lower degree of something. Used in formal, old-fashioned styles. In spoken Japanese, ...どころか is used instead.

【ひとつ】

1. ひとつ...ない

Emphasizes the absence of something. Similar expressions such as ...も...ない, ...として...ない are also used. To express frequency, 一度も／一回も／一ぺんも ...ない are used.

a. Nひとつ...ない

［Nひとつない］

［NひとつV-ない］

（1）雲 一 つない青空 。／Cloudless blue sky.

（2）しみひとつない美 しい肌 。／Beautiful skin without a single blemish.

（3）街 は清潔 で、ちりひとつ落 ちていない。／The town is so clean that not a piece of rubbish is to be found.

（4）夜 の公園 には、猫 の仔 一匹 いなかった。／There wasn’t a single cat in the park at night.

（5）あたりはしーんとして、物音 ひとつしない。／The area was perfectly still and not a sound was heard.

（6）彼 の意見 に誰 一人 反対 しなかった。／Not one person objected to his opinion.

（7）昨日 から何 ひとつ食 べていない。／I haven’t eaten a thing since yesterday.

Means “there is absolutely no ....” As in the case of (1) and (2), by stating that there are no clouds/blemishes, the blueness of the sky and the beauty of the skin are emphasized. In the cases of (3)-(5), when using a verb, the expression becomes a negative of the verb, “not at all V.” As a counter, apart from ひとつ, “one + counter” (such as 一匹、一人、一枚) is often used. Also, as in the cases of (6) and (7), 誰ひとり...ない and 何ひとつ...ない emphasize the meaning of “nobody” and “nothing.”

b. ...ひとつも...ない

［ひとつもない］

［ひとつも　A-くない］

［ひとつも　V-ない］

（1）知 った顔 はひとつもない。／There is no one I recognize.

（2）この料理 はひとつもうまくない。／There’s nothing tasty with this food.

（3）彼 の作文 には、まちがいはひとつもなかった。／His essay didn’t have a single mistake.

（4）このごろのファッションなんか、ひとつもいいと思 わない。／I don’t think fashions these days have anything good about them.

（5）あいつは、君 の忠告 なんかひとつも覚 えてやしないよ。／He won’t remember anything you warned him about.

Emphasizes that “there is no N” or “it is not A/not V.”

2. もうひとつ／いまひとつ　...ない

（1）給料 はいいが、仕事 の内容 がもうひとつ気 に入 らない。／The pay is good but the contents of the job are not quite satisfying.

（2）風邪 がもうひとつよくならない。／I just can’t shake off this cold.

（3）今年 のみかんは、甘味 がもうひとつ足 りない。／This year’s oranges are not quite sweet enough.

（4）今年 のみかんは、甘味 がもうひとつだ。／This year’s oranges don’t have the sweetness I want.

Used in the patterns もうひとつ...ない or 今ひとつ...ない and indicates that something has not reached the level the speaker had expected. The situation is not bad, but at the same time the level achieved is not sufficient or satisfactory. (1) means that the speaker does not like the contents of the job very much. (2) means that the speaker’s cold isn’t completely better. (3) and (4) mean that the oranges are slightly lacking in sweetness.

3. Nひとつ...できない

（1）近 ごろの子供 はぞうきんひとつ満足 にしぼれない。／Children nowadays can’t even wring a cloth properly.

（2）女優 のくせに、歌 ひとつ歌 えない。／Even though she’s an actress, she can’t even sing anything.

（3）このごろの若 いやつは、挨拶 ひとつ満足 にできない。／Young people these days can’t even greet others properly.

（4）留学 してから、もう半年 にもなるのに、息子 ははがきひとつよこさない。／My son has been abroad studying for six months already but has yet to send even a postcard.

（5）ビール一杯 飲 めないようでは、社会 にでてから困 るだろう。／You will have problems when you go out into the world if you can’t drink even a glass of beer.

（6）当時 はたいへん貧 しく、子供達 に着物 一枚 新 しく買 ってやれなかった。／In those days we were so poor that we couldn’t even buy any new clothes for our children.

Used to emphasize the fact that a simple thing cannot be achieved or accomplished on this occasion, even though it would have been possible in any other situation. Often used to express the speaker’s disapproval or criticism by implying that any more than what has been stated is not achievable.

4. ひとつ

（1）ひとつよろしくお願 いしますよ。／Could you please do me a favor?

（2）ひとつ頼 まれてほしいことがあるんだが。／There is something I would like you to help me with.

（3）ひとつ頼 まれてくれないか。／Will you do something for me?

（4）ここはひとつやってみるか。／Shall we have a go at this?

（5）ひとつ話 にのってみようか。／Shall I take up the suggestion?

（6）おひとつどうぞ。／Please have one (food or drink).

（7）ひとついかがですか。／Would you like to try one/some?

Used idiomatically in conversation. Means “try, have a go.” Used in requests as in the cases of examples (1) - (3), or in describing trying something as in the case of examples (4) and (5). Also used when offering food or drink as shown in examples (6) and (7).

【ほとんど】

1. ほとんど

（1）この小説 はほとんど読 んでしまった。／I have almost finished reading this novel.

（2）京都 の有名 な寺 にはほとんどいったことがある。／I have visited almost all the famous temples in Kyoto.

（3）新 しいビルは、ほとんど完成 している。／The new building is almost completed.

（4）彼 ほどの成績 なら、合格 はほとんど確実 だ。／Judging by his academic record, it is almost certain that he will pass the examination.

（5）地域 のスポーツクラブに行 ってみたら、ほとんどが年輩 の人 だったのには驚 いた。／I was surprised to find that there were mainly elderly people at the local sports club.

（6）このクラスのほとんどが、アジアからの留学生 だ。／Most students in this class are from Asian countries.

Means “almost” or “the majority.” Being used to modify the predicate of the sentence as in the cases of examples (1) - (3), it can mean “not entirely, but almost all” or “almost 100%” as in the case of (4). It can also be used in the form of （Nの）ほとんどが indicating “most of N” as in the cases of (5) and (6).

2. ほとんど...ない

（1）給料日 前 でほとんど金 がない。／Since it is a few days before I get paid, I have very little money at the moment.

（2）彼 は酒 はほとんど飲 まない。／He hardly drinks any alcohol.

（3）英語 はほとんど読 めない。／I can hardly read any English.

（4）この仕事 を三日 で仕上 げるのは、ほとんど不可能 に近 い。／It would be almost impossible to complete this task within three days.

（5）このごろは忙 しくて、あれほど好 きだったテニスにも、ほとんど行 っていない。／I have been so busy lately that I’ve hardly had time to play tennis, which I used to enjoy so much.

（6）今 でこそ有名 だが、10 年 ほど前 には、彼 の名前 を知 っている人 は、ほとんどいなかった。／He is now very famous, but ten or so years ago, there was hardly anyone who knew his name.

（7）ほとんど飲 まず食 わずで、一日中 働 き続 けた。／I continued to work all day, almost without eating or drinking.

（8）遭難 して三日 めには、食糧 もほとんどなくなった。／By the third day after we’d lost our way, the food was almost gone.

Means that the amount is very little, or the frequency is low.

3. ほとんど...た

［ほとんどV-るところだった］

［ほとんどR-かけた］

（1）子供 の頃 、チフスでほとんど死 にかけたことがある。／I nearly died from typhoid fever when I was a child.

（2）横道 から飛 び出 してきた自転車 とほとんどぶつかるところだった。／I nearly collided with a bicycle that came speeding out of a side road.

（3）事業 は、ほとんどうまくいきかけたのだが、運悪 く得意先 が倒産 してしまい、それからは悪 いこと続 きだった。／We nearly made a success of the business, but unfortunately one of the customers went bankrupt, and after that there was nothing but trouble.

Means that something looked very likely to happen but in reality it did not. Often used in the sense of a narrow escape, as in the cases of examples (1) and (2).

【また】

1. また

a. また〈repetition〉

（1）また、飛行機 が落 ちたらしい。／It seems that another plane has crashed.

（2）同 じ問題 をまた間違 えた。／I got the same question wrong again.

（3）A:すみません。来週 の金曜日 、休 ませていただきたいのですが。／Excuse me. If possible I’d take like to take a day off next Friday.

B:またですか。先週 も休 んだでしょう。／Again? You took it off last week, too, didn’t you?

（4）A:さようなら、また来 てくださいね。／Goodbye. Please come again, OK?

B:有難 うございます。また、おじゃまします。／Thank you very much. I would love to come again.

（5）《授業 の終 わりに》では、また来週 。／《at the end of a class》Well, see you again next week.

（6）A:じゃ、また。／Okay, see you again.

B:じゃあね。／See you!

Demonstrates the repeated occurrence of the same thing. As in (4)-(6), it is also used as a parting salutation.

b. また〈adjunction〉

（1）教科書 は、大学 生協 で購入 できる。また、大 きな書店 でも販売 している。／You can purchase the textbook at the university cooperative. It is also sold at large bookstores.

（2）10 月 から大手 私鉄 の運賃 が平均 20 ％値上 げされる。また、地下鉄 、市 バスも来年 4月 に値上 げを予定 している。／Beginning in October, the major private railway companies will raise their fares by an average of 20%. Moreover, there are also plans to raise subway and city bus fares starting in April of next year.

（3）《テレビのニュースで》現在 、新幹線 は京都 神戸 間 が不通 になっております。また、在来線 は大阪 神戸 間 が不通 となっております。／《television news》The shinkansen (bullet train) service between Kyoto and Kobe is currently suspended. Additionally, service on all other railway lines between Osaka and Kobe has also been suspended.

（4）《テレビのニュースで》天皇 皇后 両陛下 の韓国 御訪問 は、10 月 と決 まりました。また、首席 随行員 は渡辺 外相 が務 めます。／《television news》The visit of Their Majesties, the Emperor and Empress, to Korea has been arranged for October. Furthermore, Foreign Minister Watanabe will serve as their chief attendant.

Used to give further explanation or to add new information in connection to a matter already related.

c. また〈list〉

（1）彼 は良 き父 であり、また良 き夫 でもある。／He is a good father and also a good husband.

（2）この本 はおもしろく、またためになる。／This book is interesting and also educational.

（3）喫煙 は健康 に悪 いし、また、周囲 の迷惑 にもなる。／Smoking is bad for your health and also a nuisance to those around you.

Means “in addition...” or “moreover....” Used to list similar matters or information. Often used in the form また...も.

d. また〈choice〉

（1）参加 してもよい。また、参加 しなくてもよい。／It’s okay if you participate. It’s also okay if you don’t.

（2）黒 か青 のインクで書 くこと。また、パソコンの使用 も可 。／Write in black or blue ink. Alternatively, it is also acceptable to use a personal computer.

Means “one of two (options).” Often used in the form また...も.

2. ...もまた

［Nもまた］

［Na なのもまた］

［A／V　のもまた］

（1）山 でのキャンプ生活 は電気 もガスもないが、不便 なのもまた楽 しい。／When camping in the mountains there is no electricity or gas, but there’s also something fun about the inconvenience.

（2）暑 いのも困 るが寒 いのもまたたいへんだ。／The heat is troublesome but the cold is just as much a problem.

（3）晴 れた日 の散歩 は楽 しい。しかし、雨 にぬれながら歩 くのもまた風情 があっていいものだ。／A walk on a clear day is enjoyable. However, walking while getting wet in the rain also has its attractions.

（4）天才 といえども、彼 もまた人 の子 だ。うれしいときもあれば悲 しいときもある。／A genius though he is, he is also human. He has both happy times and sad times.

Means “in the same way,” or “just as.” As in (1) - (3), it introduces a thing which is similar to that previously related. In the case of (4) it means “even a genius like him is the same as normal people.”

3. ...また

（1）いったいまたどうしてそんなことを。／Why (on earth) would you do that kind of thing?

（2）どうしてまた、こんなことになったのだろうか。／Why (on earth) has this kind of thing happened?

（3）しかしよくまた、こんなことができたものだ。／It is amazing how anyone could have done such a thing!

（4）これはまたきれいな絵 ですね。／This is such a beautiful picture, isn’t it?

When used together with phrases such as いったい, どうして, and これは, shows the speaker’s feeling of surprise or wonder.

4. またのN

（1）またのお越 しをお待 ちしております。／We look forward to serving you again.

（2）きょうは忙 しいので、この話 はまたの機会 にお願 いします。／Since today is very busy, I would like to discuss this matter at some other opportunity.

（3）彼 は医者 だが、またの名 を北山 淳 といって有名 な小説家 でもある。／He is a doctor but he is also a famous novelist by the name of Kitayama Jun.

Means “the next” or “another” (occasion). Examples (1) and (2) are common set phrases limited to use with nouns such as “another opportunity/chance/time/day/name.” またの名を...という in (3) means “(his) other name is.../also known as....”

5. NまたN

（1）一行 は、山 また山 の奥地 に進 んで行 った。／The party proceeded into the mountainous interior.

（2）残業 また残業 で休 む暇 もない。／I have no time to rest because I am constantly working overtime.

（3）人 また人 で歩 くこともできない。／With people on top of people, it’s impossible to walk.

By repeating the same noun, demonstrates a situation in which the same things form a series/chain or a situation in which the same thing continues.

【まったく】

1. まったく...ない

（1）きのうのクラスはまったくおもしろくなかった。／Yesterday’s class was not at all interesting.

（2）彼 は家 ではまったく勉強 をしない。／He does not study at all at home.

（3）この一週間 全 く雨 が降 っていない。／It hasn’t rained at all this week.

（4）その選手 のフォームは全 く文句 のつけようのない美 しさだ。／The beauty of that player’s form cannot be criticized.

（5）そのバイオリニストのアルバムは、デビューアルバムとしては全 く申 し分 のない出来 である。／One cannot say anything bad about that violinist’s album as a debut album.

Used to emphasize the negative meaning. It is more formal than ぜんぜん, すこしも and ちっとも, etc. In order to intensify phrases such as 文句のつけようがない, 申し分のない, and 非の打ち所がない, etc., it is difficult to use any expression other than まったく.

2. まったく

（1）これとこれはまったく同 じものです。／This and this are entirely the same.

（2）それとこれとはまったくちがう話 だ。／That and this are completely different conversations.

（3）まったくいやな雨 だなあ。／This rain is so unpleasant.

（4）またお金 わすれたの？　まったくこまった人 ね。／You forgot your money again? You really are impossible.

（5）A:うっとうしい天気 だね。／What miserable weather!

B:まったくだ。／You said it!

（6）きのうの演奏 は全 くすばらしいものだった。／Yesterday’s performance was absolutely wonderful.

Used to emphasize the extent of something. In example (5) it is used to give strong affirmation in response to what the other person has said.

【もう2】

1. もう〈completion〉

（1）今日 の仕事 はもう全部 終 わった。／Today’s work is all done.

（2）A:今 評判 になっているあの映画 、もう見 ましたか。／Have you seen that film that everyone’s talking about now?

B:ええ、この前 の日 曜日 に見 ました。／Yes, I watched it last Sunday.

（3）食事 はもうできている。／Dinner is ready.

（4）その問題 なら、もう解決 している。／That problem? It’s been resolved already.

（5）彼 の娘 はもう大学 を卒業 したそうだ。／I heard that his daughter has already graduated from college.

（6）駅 についたときにもう特急 は出 てしまっていた。／When I got to the station, the limited express had already left.

（7）手紙 はもう投函 したので、取 り返 せないんです。／I have already mailed the letter, so I can’t get it back.

（8）A:すみません、今日 はもう閉店 ですか。／Excuse me, are you already closed for today?

B:いいえ、まだ開 いています。／No, we’re still open.

（9）A:この本 はもう出 ましたか。／Is this book out yet?

B:いいえ、まだ出 ていません。予定 は来週 です。／No, not yet. It is scheduled (to be out) next week.

When used with a verb phrase, this indicates the completion of a deed or event by a certain point in time. It is also used in interrogative sentences asking whether or not something has been completed. When the point of completion has not yet been reached, まだ...ない is used in both declarative and interrogative sentences.

2. もう　+時 間 ／+年 齢

（1）おしゃべりに夢中 になっていたら、もう5時 だ。／We got lost in conversation and it’s already five o’clock.

（2）気 がついたらもう朝 だった。／Before we knew it, it was already morning.

（3）この子 はもう 10 才 だから、十分 事故 の証人 になれる。／This child is already ten years old, so she can serve as a witness to an accident.

（4）こよみの上 ではもう春 なのに、まだ雪 が降 っている。／Although the calendar says it is spring, it is still snowing.

（5）もう夜 が明 けるのに彼 らはまだ話 し続 けている。／They kept on talking even though dawn was breaking.

（6）もう8時 ですよ。起 きなさい、学校 に遅 れますよ。／It’s already eight o’clock. Get up, or you’ll be late for school.

Used with expressions which show time or age, it shows that a point which is rather late has been reached. As in examples (1) and (2), it includes the feeling that a certain point in time has been reached sooner than was thought.

3. もうNa だ／もういい

（1）もうおなかが一杯 だ。／I’m already full.

（2）今日 はもう十分 に楽 しんだ。／I’ve already had a lot of fun today.

（3）A:お湯 はわいていますか。／Is the water boiling yet?

B:ええ、もういいですよ。／Yes, it’s ready.

（4）A:機械 、直 ったんですか。／Is the machine fixed?

B:ええ、これでもういいはずです。／Yes, it should be fine now.

（5）A:ちょっと目 を閉 じて。1、2、3。／Just shut your eyes. One, two, three.

B:もういい？／Okay now?

A:いいよ。はい、目 を開 けて。／Okay, open your eyes.

Used with phrases such as 一杯だ and 十分だ, this means “(it) ought to be enough/satisfactory.” もういい, basically meaning “a satisfactory situation or state has been reached,” is used in various circumstances. Depending on the context, it can mean “to have done enough,” or “to have resolved (it).” For the negative usage rules for もういい, please see Usage 5b of もう.

4. もう...ない

（1）山田 さんはもうここにはいません。／Yamada-san is no longer here.

（2）この喫茶店 はもう営業 していない。／This coffee shop is no longer in business.

（3）疲 れて、もう何 も考 えられなくなった。／I was so tired I couldn’t think anymore.

（4）交渉 のあと、だれももう文句 を言 わなかった。／After the negotiations, nobody had any more complaints.

（5）かれとは、もうこれ以上 話 したくない。／I don’t want to say anything more to him.

（6）わたしは、18 才 、もう子供 ではない。／I’m eighteen. I’m not a child anymore.

（7）もう二度 とあの人 には会 わないだろう。／I don’t suppose I’ll ever meet her again.

（8）もう誰 も信 じられないと言 って、彼女 は泣 いていた。／She was crying and said, “I can’t trust anyone anymore.”

（9）こんな待遇 の悪 い職場 にはもうがまんができない。／I can’t take it anymore in a workplace like this with such terrible conditions.

（10）さいふの中 にはもう 100 円 しか残 っていなかったので、家 へ帰 るのにバスにも乗 れなかった。／Since I only had 100 yen left in my wallet, I couldn’t even catch the bus home.

（11）10 万 円 の値段 がついたので、もうこれ以上 は上 がらないだろうと思 った。／Because it was already priced at 100,000 yen, I didn’t think the price could go any higher.

This means, with something like a certain point in time as the limit, there is nothing further or nothing after that.

5. もう〈negative attitude〉

a. もう+否 定 的 表 現

（1）こんな退屈 な仕事 はもうやめたい。／I want to quit this kind of boring work.

（2）もうあの人 の愚痴 を聞 くのはいやだ。／I’m sick of hearing that person’s complaints.

（3）これ以上 歩 き続 けるのは体力的 にもう無理 です。／It’s physically impossible for me to walk any further.

（4）あの人 をかばい続 けられるのももう限界 だ。／I can’t carry on sticking up for that man.

（5）戦争 をするのは、もうたくさんだ。／I’ve had it with the war.

（6）こんなまずいものを食 べるのはもうたくさんだ。／I can’t eat any more of such disgusting stuff.

（7）もういいかげんに妹 をいじめるのはやめなさい。／Stop picking on your younger sister.

Using predicates with a negative meaning such as 無理だ and いやだ, this means the situation cannot be tolerated any further. Meaning “the limit has been reached and so I can’t take anymore,” もうたくさんだ is often used when the speaker is feeling quite emotional. It can also be used in cases, such as example (7), which prohibit further such behavior.

b. もういい

（1）A:ほかに出 す書類 がありますか。／Do you have any other documents to hand in?

B:これでもういいです。／That’s all.

（2）A:チョコレート買 いましょうか。／Shall we buy some chocolate?

B:いや、これだけ食料 があれば、もういいです。／No, this should be enough food.

（3）A:もう一杯 いかがですか。／How about one more (glass/cup)?

B:いや、もういいです。／No, I’ve had enough.

（4）A:急 なアルバイトさえなかったら、来 られたんだけど。／If I just hadn’t had that sudden part-time work, I could have come.

B:言 い訳 はもういいよ。／That’s enough of your excuses.

（5）A:お母 さんの気持 ちも考 えてみなさい。／Try to think about your mother’s feelings, too.

B:もういいよ。お説教 は聞 き飽 きたよ。／Enough! I’m tired of your preaching!

（6）A:頑張 っていたのに、うまく行 かなくて残念 だったね。／It’s such a shame that it didn’t go well even though you did your best.

B:もういいんです。何 か、ほかの事 を考 えます。／Oh, it’s okay. I will think of something else.

（7）A:もう一回 探 しなおせば、みつかるかもしれません。／If we have another look, we may be able to find it.

B:もういいよ。あきらめよう。／I’ve had enough! Let’s give it up.

Fundamentally this means “because this is enough, more than this is not necessary.” It is used in various circumstances. In example (3) it is used to decline something. Also, in (4) and (5), meaning “this is the limit, I can’t accept more than this,” it conveys the speaker’s attitude of refusal. It is often used in cases in which something has become disagreeable or tedious. As in (6) and (7), it is also used as an expression which conveys the feeling of being sick of or giving up on something which had been adhered to until that point. For the affirmative usage rules of もういい, see Usage 3 of もう.

6. もう〈criticism〉

（1）お母 さんたら、もう。わたしの友達 の悪口 を言 うのはやめてよ。／Mom, enough! Stop badmouthing my friends.

（2）もう、あなたったら、こんなやさしい計算 もできないの。／Oh, come on, dear. Can’t you even do a simple calculation like this?

（3）山田 さんたら、もう、また「お茶入 れて」ですって。自分 でやればいいのに。／That Yamada-san telling me again, “Make some tea.” He should make it himself.

（4）A:あ、また、汚 した。／Oh, it’s dirty again.

B:もう。／Already again!

At the start or in the middle of a sentence, this expresses a feeling of criticism towards the other person. Only used in casual conversation and is often used by women. Frequently used with the highly critical (っ)たら.

【もしかしたら】

1. もしかしたら...かもしれない

（1）仕事 の量 が減 ったから、もしかしたらわたしも日曜日 に出 かけられるかもしれない。／My workload has lessened and so perhaps I might be able to go out on Sunday.

（2）今 はいい天気 だが、すこし雲 が出 て来 たから、もしかしたら雨 が降 るかもしれない。／It is nice weather now, but clouds are gathering and it might rain.

（3）この名刺 があれば、もしかしたら、彼 に面会 できるかもしれない。／If I have this business card, perhaps I might be able to meet with him.

（4）彼 はここ2、3日 大学 に出 て来 ない。もしかしたら彼 は病気 かもしれない。／He hasn’t been to college classes for two or three days. Perhaps he’s sick.

（5）もしかしたら、中田 さんが知 っているかもしれないが、はっきりしたことはまだわからない。／Perhaps Nakata-san knows, but I’m still really not sure.

（6）もしかしたら、山川 さんがその本 をもっているのではないだろうか。／Could Yamakawa-san maybe have that book?

When accompanied by conjectural phrases such as ...かもしれない and ...のではないだろうか, expresses the supposition that “that too might be possible.” Indicates the speaker’s lack of confidence in his/her own judgment. もしかすると, もしかして, and ひょっとすると are also used.

2. もしかしたら...か

（1）A:あの人 、もしかしたら、山本 さんじゃないですか。／That person, might it possibly be Yamamoto-san?

B:ええ。そうですよ。ご存 じですか。／Yes, it is. Do you know her?

（2）もしかしたら事故 にでもあったんじゃない？／Has there been an accident or something?

（3）もしかしたら今日 は雨 になるのではないだろうか。／Don’t you think it might turn to rain today?

Used with phrases which express a question, such as ...か and じゃない？, demonstrates the speaker’s lack of confidence in his/her own judgment. もしかすると, もしかして, and ひょっとして are also used.

【ものか】

［Na なものか］

［A-いものか］

［V-るものか］

1. ...ものか／...もんか

（1）A:はさみも持 って行 く？／Are you taking scissors?

B:そんなもの必要 なもんか。／Why would that be necessary?

（2）A:藤井 さんが一番 になったそうね。／They say Fujii-san has become number one.

B:そんなことがあるもんか。何 かの間違 いだろう。／That can’t be! There must be some kind of mistake.

（3）こんな複雑 な文章 、訳 せるものですか。／There is no way such a complicated sentence can be translated.

（4）誘 われたって、だれが行 くものか。／Even if they invited me, there’s no way I would go.

（5）あんな人 に、頼 むもんか。／There is no way I would ask such a person a favor.

（6）誰 が人 に手渡 したりするものですか。／There is no way I would hand this over to someone else.

With a falling intonation, expresses a feeling of strong denial. Examples (4)-(6) express the speaker’s strong intention that something will not be done. Used in casual conversation.

Usually, ものか is used by men and the polite ものですか is used by women.

2. V-ないものだろうか

（1）もう少 し涼 しくならないものかなあ。／I wish it would get a little cooler.

（2）もう少 し分 かりやすく書 けなかったものか。／Couldn’t you have written it (in a way that would have been) a little easier to understand?

（3）何 とかして晩 までに青森 まで行 けないものか考 えてみよう。／Let’s think if there is a way for us to get to Aomori by evening.

（4）だれかに協力 してもらえないものだろうか。／Can’t I get some cooperation from somebody on this?

（5）2時間 の通勤 時間 を何 とか利用 できないものかと考 えた。／I thought about whether there was some way I could take advantage of my two-hour commute.

（6）A:彼 と話 しができないものでしょうか。／I wonder if we could talk to him.

B:何 とか方法 を考 えましょう。／Let me think of some way to do that.

Shows that the speaker wishes for a certain event to take place. The ...なかったものか in example (2) contains a feeling of bewilderment that something has not taken place. Also, when used with the sentence ending (と)考える, means that whether or not the realization of an event or occurrence is possible is being considered. Can also be used, as in (6), to make a tentative request.

3. どうしたもの（だろう）か

（1）反対派 への説明 はどうしたものかね。／How are we supposed to explain this to the opposition?

（2）彼 らに対 する報酬 はどうしたものだろうか。／What should I do to remunerate them?

（3）今後 の資金繰 りはどうしたものか、少 し考 えさせてくれ。／Let me think a little about what we should do for funding from now on.

Expresses a feeling of confusion over what the best course of action is. Can also be used as a question of someone present.

【ものがある】

［Na なものがある］

［A-いものがある］

［V-るものがある］

（1）この作品 は発想 に斬新 なものがある。／There is an originality of conception to this work.

（2）彼 の潜在 能力 にはすばらしいものがある。／He has wonderful potential.

（3）この文章 はまだまだ未熟 だが、しかし随所 にキラリと光 るものがある。／This composition is still not polished, but there are flashes of brilliance everywhere.

（4）彼女 の企画書 は結局 通 らなかったが、いくつかの点 で見 るべきものがある。／In the end, her (business) proposal was not accepted, but there were some points that were commendable.

Means that certain characteristics are evident. The 見るべきもの in example (4) means “excellent points that are notable.” In place of ある, forms such as 見られる and 認められる can also be used.

（例）この文章はまだまだ未熟だが、しかし随所にキラリと光るものが見られる。／This composition is still not polished, but you can see flashes of brilliance everywhere.

Has the tone of written language.

【ものでもない】

1. V-たものでもない

（1）しろうとばかりの劇 だが、すぐれたところもあり、そう馬鹿 にしたものでもない。／It was an all-amateur play but there were some excellent parts, so it isn’t to be belittled.

（2）みんな、主任 になったばかりの佐々木 さんを若 すぎて頼 りないと言 うが、彼 の行動力 はそう見 くびったものでもない。／Everyone is saying that Sasaki-san, who has just taken charge, is too young and lacking in leadership qualities, but her dynamism is not to be underrated.

（3）年 をとったといっても、わたしのテニスの腕 はまだまだ捨 てたものではない。／You could say I’ve gotten old, but my tennis skills are not to be underestimated.

With expressions containing the meaning “to slight,” expresses the meaning that something is “not that bad.”

2. V-ないものでもない

（1）この程度 の料理 なら、私 にも作 れないものでもない。／If it’s only that level of cooking, (perhaps) even I could make it.

（2）道 は険 しいが、気 をつけて歩 いて行 けば行 けないものでもない。／The route is steep, but if we walk carefully, we should be able to get there.

（3）理由 次第 では、手 を貸 さないものでもない。／Depending on your reasons, I might consider helping you.

（4）このルートで休 みなしに走 れば、間 に合 わぬものでもない。／If we run this route without taking a break, we might possibly make it on time.

Conservatively expresses that something “can” be done. A formal, somewhat old-fashioned phrase. Fundamentally the same as V-なくもない.

【やなんぞ】

［Nやなんぞ］

（1）大学 の名前 やなんぞでぼくを評価 してほしくない。／I don’t want to be judged on things like the name of my university.

（2）不況 やなんぞには負 けていられない。皆 で会社 のためにがんばろう。／We cannot be defeated by things like a recession. Let’s all do our best for the company.

（3）塾 やなんぞに行 っても、やる気 がなくちゃだめだ。／Even if you go to cram school or whatever, it’s no good if you have no motivation.

（4）たった一度 の受賞 やなんぞで得意 になってはいけないよ。／You really shouldn’t let getting an award once go to your head.

Means ...やなにか but is used negatively. やなんか can also be used. A somewhat old-fashioned expression.

【ように3】

1. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）〈purpose〉

（1）後 ろの席 の人 にも聞 こえるように大 きな声 で話 した。／I said it in a loud enough voice so that even the people in the seats behind could hear it.

（2）子供 にも読 めるよう名前 にふりがなをつけた。／I put my name in furigana so that even children would be able to read it.

（3）赤 ん坊 を起 こさないようにそっと布団 を出 た。／I got out of the futon softly, so as not to wake the baby.

（4）忘 れないようにノートにメモしておこう。／I will make a note of this so I won’t forget.

Using a verb before and after, this means “do... so as to make such a circumstance or situation occur/do... so as not to....”に is sometimes omitted. Before ように, verbs which show non-volitional actions, such as なる and できる, or verbs which show possibility in the form V-れる are often used, as are the negative forms of verbs and expressions which show the state or condition of a thing. The clause which follows ように is a verb which demonstrates the speaker’s intentional act. The subject may differ before and after, as in examples (1)-(3), or it may be the same, as in (4).

Furthermore, in cases where the subject is the same before and after, and where the first verb demonstrates an intentional action, it is usual to use ために.

（×）息子が家で仕事ができるために父親は家を改築した。（異主語･非意志的）／So that his son could work from home, the father renovated the house. (different subject, non-volitional)

（○）息子が家で仕事ができるように父親は家を改築した。（異主語･非意志的）／So that his son could work from home, the father renovated the house. (different subject, non-volitional)

（○）家で仕事をするために家を改築した。（同一主語・意志的）／He renovated the house so he could work from home. (same subject, volitional)

2. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）〈admonition〉

（1）忘 れ物 をしないようにしてください。／Don’t leave anything behind.

（2）時間内 に終了 するようお願 いします。／Please finish within the time (allowed).

（3）風邪 をひかないようご注意 ください。／Please take care not to catch a cold.

（4）私語 は慎 むようにしなさい。／Please refrain from whispering amongst yourselves.

（5）集合 時間 は守 るように。／Keep to the appointed time.

（6）授業中 はおしゃべりしないように。／No chatting during class.

Used to give advice to or to remonstrate with the listener. Verbs such as しなさい／してください and お願いします are used in the latter half but are sometimes omitted, in which case the expression ends with ように. Also, it is possible to omit the に from ように but, where the sentence ends with ように, it is usual not to do so, as in examples (5) and (6). Used in the form V-ないように, this often expresses negative advice or recommendations.

3. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）〈prayer〉

（1）息子 が大学 に合格 できるよう神 に祈 った。／I prayed to God that my son would pass the university entrance exam.

（2）現状 がさらに改善 されるよう期待 している。／I hope that the present situation will improve again.

（3）《年賀状 》新 しい年 が幸 い多 き年 でありますよう祈 っております。／《New Year’s card》Wishing you a joyful new year.

（4）《病気 見舞 の手紙 》早 く全快 なさいますよう、祈念 いたしております。／《get-well card》I am praying for your swift and complete recovery.　

（5）どうか合格 できますように。／Wishing you success in the (e.g. entrance) exams.

（6）すべてがうまくいきますよう。／Hoping all goes well.

（7）あしたは雨 が降 りませんように。／Praying that it does not rain tomorrow.

Expresses one’s or another’s hopes, prayers and wishes. Verbs such as 祈る(pray), 祈念する(say a prayer), 念じる(pray silently), 望む(desire), 願う(wish), 希望する(hope) and 期待する(expect) are used after ように. As in examples (5) and (6), the expression can end with ように. In such cases the polite form is usually used before ように. It is often used to bring a speech or letter to a close.

4. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）いう

（1）すぐ家 に帰 るように言 われました。／I was told to go home at once.

（2）これからは遅刻 しないように注意 しておきました。／I warned them not to be late from now on.

（3）戻 りましたら、家 に電話 するようお伝 えください。／Please tell him to call me at home when he comes back (to the office).　

（4）隣 の人 に、ステレオの音量 を下 げてもらうように頼 んだ。／I asked my neighbor to turn the volume of her stereo down.

Using verbs of communication, such as 言う(say) and 伝える(convey) in the latter half, this is used to indirectly quote a request. Direct quotations take the following form: command/request+と+verb of communication.

（例）「すぐ帰れ」と言った。／She said, “Go home at once.”

（例）「ステレオの音量を下げてください」と頼んだ。／I asked, “Please would you turn down the volume of your stereo?”

5. V-る／V-ない　ようにする

（1）私 は肉 を小 さく切 って、こどもにも食 べられるようにした。／I cut the meat into small pieces so that even children could eat it.

（2）大 きな活字 を使 い、老人 にも読 みやすいようにする。／We use large print so that it’s easy for the elderly to read.

（3）できるだけ英会話 のテレビを見 るようにしている。／I’m watching as much English conversation program on TV as I possibly can.

（4）彼女 の機嫌 を損 ねることは言 わないようにした。／I tried not to say things that would hurt her feelings.

（5）試験日 には、目覚 まし時計 を2台 セットして寝坊 しないようにしよう。／On exams days I set two alarm clocks so that I don’t overlay.

（6）油 ものは食 べないようにしている。／I try not to eat fried foods.

Means to make efforts with the aim of/to aim to/to see to it that an action or situation occurs. As in examples (4)-(6), when the negative form is used, it means to aim for the action or situation not to occur....ようにしている of (3) and (6) means to do that thing customarily. A verb usually comes before ように but, as in example (2), V-やすい is also used. In this case 読みやすくする could also be used.

6. V-る／V-ない　ようになる

（1）日本語 が話 せるようになりました。／I have become able to speak Japanese.

（2）眼鏡 をかければ、黒板 の字 が見 えるようになります。／I can see the letters on the blackboard if I wear my glasses.

（3）赤 ちゃんはずいぶん活発 に動 くようになりました。／The baby has started moving very vigorously.

（4）隣 の子供 は最近 きちんとあいさつするようになった。／The neighbor’s child has recently begun to make the proper greetings.

（5）注意 したら文句 を言 わないようになった。／After I had a word, he stopped complaining.

Taking the dictionary form of verbs, expresses a change from a situation in which something is not possible to one in which it is, or, from one in which a thing cannot be realized to one in which it can. It is often used to express possibility in the form V-れる, as in example (1). In cases where the negative form is used, as in (5), it expresses a change to a situation in which a thing is not done. In this case 言わなくなった could also be said.

【ろく】

1. ろくなN...ない

（1）こんな安月給 ではろくな家 に住 めない。／I can’t live in a decent home on such a low salary.

（2）誰 もこの言葉 を知 らないのか。まったくこの課 にはろくな奴 がいないな。／Isn’t there anyone who knows this word? I swear, there really is no one I can count on in this department.

（3）上司 には怒 られるし、彼女 にはふられるし、ろくなことがない。／My boss is mad at me, my girlfriend’s giving me the cold shoulder—nothing’s any good.

（4）A:どうもごちそうさまでした。／Thank you. That was a feast.

B:いいえ、最近 ろくなおかまいもできませんで。／Don’t mention it—I haven’t done anything special for you recently.

Shows an unsatisfactory or worse than average thing.

2. ろくでもないN

（1）花子 はろくでもない男 に夢中 になっている。／Hanako is infatuated with a good-for-nothing man.

（2）そんなろくでもない本 ばかり読 んでいるから、成績 が悪 くなるのよ。／Because you only read such worthless books, your grades are suffering.

（3）A:そんなに仕事 がいやなら、早 いとこお見合 いでもして結婚 したらどう。／If you dislike work so much, how about quickly having an arranged marriage?

B:そんなろくでもないこと言 わないでよ。／Don’t say such stupid things!

Expresses that a thing is worthless, good-for-nothing, or stupid.

3. ろくに V-ない

（1）テストも近 いというのに、あの子 ったらろくに勉強 もしないんだから。／Even though the test is soon, that child will not study enough.

（2）あいつは昼間 から酒 ばかり飲 んでろくに仕事 もしないくせに、食 べるときは人一倍 食 べる。／Even though that guy just only drinks sake from noontime on and hardly does any worthwhile work, when it’s time to eat he puts away as much as anyone.

（3）せっかく海 に来 たというのに、彼女 はろくに泳 ぎもしないで肌 を焼 いてばかりいた。／We finally came to the sea but she hardly swam at all and just sunbathed.

（4）ろくに予習 しなくたって、あの授業 は先生 がやさしいから何 とかなる。／I haven’t prepared enough but the teacher of that class is easy-going so I’ll manage somehow.

（5）そんな雑誌 、ろくに読 まなくてもだいたいどんなことが書 いてあるかは見当 が付 くよ。／Even without reading much of that kind of magazine, I have a general idea of what sort of things are written in it.

Shows that something is not done to one’s satisfaction. Means “almost not...” and “not (done) enough.”

【わけがない】

［N　な／である　わけがない］

［Na なわけがない］

［A／V　わけがない］

（1）あいつが犯人 なわけ（が）ないじゃないか。／There’s no way that guy could be the perpetrator.

（2）A:最近 元気 ？／Have you been well lately?

B:元気 なわけ（が）ないでしょ。彼 と仲直 りできなくて、もう悲惨 な状態 なのよ。／There’s no way I could be well. I can’t make up with my boyfriend; it’s a miserable state of affairs.

（3）北海道 で熱帯 の植物 が育 つわけがない。／It’s impossible for tropical plants to grow in Hokkaido.

（4）こんな忙 しい時期 にスキーに行 けるわけがない。／It’s impossible for me to go skiing at such a busy time.

（5）勉強 もしないで遊 んでばかりいて、試験 にパスするわけがないじゃないか。／There’s no way you can pass the exam—not studying and just enjoying yourself all the time.

（6）考 えてみれば、彼女 が彼 に対 してそんなひどいことを言 うわけがなかった。／If you think about it, there’s no way she could have said such a horrid thing to him.

Used to strongly insist that there is no reason for such a thing to occur/no possibility of such a thing occurring. In speech, わけない is often said, with the が being omitted. It can be rephrased as はずがない.

【をたよりに】

［NをたよりにV］

（1）あなたがいなければ、これからわたしは何 をたよりに（して）生 きていけばいいのですか。／If you are not going to be there for me, what should I look up to as my guide in life?

（2）その留学生 は、辞書 をたよりに、ひとりで「橋 のない川 」を読 みつづけている。／That exchange student continues reading “The River with no Bridge” by himself with the help of a dictionary.

（3）白 いつえだけをたよりに、その人 は 70 年 生 き、そして死 んでいった。／That person lived to seventy relying solely on a white cane and then died.

（4）もちまえの行動力 だけをたよりに、彼女 はバイクで世界中 を旅 している。／She is traveling all over the world on a bike relying solely on her own resourcefulness.

Means “with the aid of something,” “depending on something.” In speech ...をたよりにして and ...をたよりとして are also used. Similar expressions are ...をたのみにして and ...をたのみとして.

【をちゅうしんに】

［NをちゅうしんにV］

（1）そのグループは山田 さんを中心 に作業 を進 めている。／With Yamada-san at the center, that group is advancing their operations.

（2）そのチームはキャプテンを中心 によくまとまったいいチームだ。／With the captain at its center, that is a well-organized, good team.

（3）太陽系 の惑星 は太陽 を中心 としてまわっている。／The solar system’s planets revolve around the sun.

（4）台風 の影響 は、九州地方 を中心 に西日本 全体 に広 がる見込 みです。／The effects of the typhoon are expected to spread over the whole of western Japan, centering on the Kyushu region.

（5）このバスは、朝 7時台 と夕方 6時台 を中心 に多 くの便数 がある。／This bus route has many services, particularly between seven and eight in the morning and six and seven in the evening.

This means “with... at the center.” This is used to show the extent of an action, phenomenon, or situation which is placed at the center/is at the core of something. It is also used in the forms ...をちゅうしんにして and ...をちゅうしんとして. Has the tone of written language.

【んじゃない】

1. んじゃない

［N／Na　（なん）じゃない］

［A／V　んじゃない］

（1）あの人 、山田 さんなんじゃない？／Isn’t that person Yamada-san?

（2）ほら、顔 があかくなった。あなた、山田 さんが好 きなんじゃないの？／Hey, you’re blushing! Is it because you like Yamada-san?

（3）それ、いいんじゃない？　悪 くないと思 うよ。／It is good, isn’t it? I don’t think it’s bad.

（4）かぎ？　テーブルの上 にあるんじゃない？／The key? Isn’t it on the table?

（5）佐藤 さん？　もう帰 ったんじゃない？／Sato-san? Hasn’t she already gone home?

An informal form of のではないか. Pronounced with a rising intonation. As in example (2), んじゃないの can also be used. Men also use んじゃないか. In polite Japanese it becomes んじゃありません.

→【ではないか2】

2. V-るんじゃない

（1）そんなところで遊 ぶんじゃない。／Don’t play in that sort of place!

（2）電車 の中 で走 るんじゃない！／No running inside the train!

（3）そんなきたないものを口 にいれるんじゃない！／Don’t put such a dirty thing in your mouth!

（4）そんな小 さい子 を突 き飛 ばすんじゃない！／Don’t push such a little child!

（5）いじめられて大 きな心 の傷 を負 っている子供 に対 して、そんなに頭 ごなしに「もっと強 くなれ」だなんて言 うんじゃないよ。／You shouldn’t keep saying things like “be stronger!” so unrelentingly to a child who has been bullied and who bears such major emotional scars.

Used to prohibit the listener’s actions. Pronounced with a falling intonation. A spoken expression used more often by men. Women often use the polite form んじゃありません.